<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A twofold catechism: the one simply called A Scripture-catechism; the other, A brief Scripture-catechism for children. Wherein the chiefest points of the Christian religion, being question-wise proposed, resolve themselves by pertinent answers taken word for word out of the Scripture, without either consequences or comments. Composed for their sakes that would fain be meer Christians, and not of this or that sect, inasmuch as all the sects of Christians, by what names soever distinguished, have either more or less departed from the simplicity and truth of the Scripture. By John Biddle, Master of Arts of the University of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Biddle, John, 1615-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1473_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209511</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868387</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76705)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 189:E1473[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A twofold catechism: the one simply called A Scripture-catechism; the other, A brief Scripture-catechism for children. Wherein the chiefest points of the Christian religion, being question-wise proposed, resolve themselves by pertinent answers taken word for word out of the Scripture, without either consequences or comments. Composed for their sakes that would fain be meer Christians, and not of this or that sect, inasmuch as all the sects of Christians, by what names soever distinguished, have either more or less departed from the simplicity and truth of the Scripture. By John Biddle, Master of Arts of the University of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Biddle, John, 1615-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 141, [11], 34, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Cottrel, for Ri. Moone, at the seven stars in Paul's Church-yard, neer the great north-door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts; "A brief Scripture-catechism for children" has been cataloged separately.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 04:th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169998:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Twofold CATECHISM: The One ſimply called <hi>A Scripture-Catechiſm;</hi> The Other, <hi>A brief Scripture-Catechiſm for Children.</hi> Wherein the chiefeſt points of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, being Queſtion-wiſe propoſed, reſolve themſelves by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Anſwers taken word for word out of the Scripture, without either Conſequences or Comments. Compoſed for their ſakes that would fain be <hi>Meer Chriſtians,</hi> and not of this or that Sect, inaſmuch as all the Sects of Chriſtians, by what names ſoever diſtinguiſhed, have either more or leſs departed from the ſimplicity and truth of the Scripture. By <hi>John Biddle,</hi> Maſter of Arts of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8. 20.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the Law, and to the Testimony: if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. Cottrel,</hi> for <hi>Ri. Moone,</hi> at the ſeven ſtars in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, neer the great North-door. 1654.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169998:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:169998:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have often wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and complained that there was no Catechiſm yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, (that I could ever ſee, or hear of) from whence one might learn the true grounds of the Chriſtian Religion, as the ſame is delivered in the holy Scripture, all Catechiſms generally being ſo ſtuffed with the ſuppoſals and traditions of men, that the leaſt part of them is derived from the Word of God. For when Councels, Convocations, &amp; Aſſemblies
<pb facs="tcp:169998:3"/> of Divines, juſtling the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writers out of their place in the Church, had once fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Articles &amp; Confeſſions of Faith according to their own fancies and intereſts, and the Civil Magiſtrate had by his Authority ratified the ſame, all Catechiſms were afterwards fitted to thoſe Articles &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, &amp; the Scripture either wholly omitted, or brought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in onely for a ſhew, not one quotation amongſt many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a whit to the purpoſe, as will ſoon appear to any man of judgment, who taking into his hand the ſaid Catechiſms, ſhall examine the texts alleged
<pb facs="tcp:169998:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> in them: for if he do this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently &amp; impartially, he will finde the Scripture and thoſe Catechiſms to be at ſo wide a diſtance one from another, that he will begin to queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Catechiſts gave any heed at all to what they wrote, and did not onely themſelves refuſe to make uſe of their Reaſon, but preſume that their Readers alſo would do the ſame. In how miſerable a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then (as to ſpiritual things) muſt Chriſtians gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally needs be, when thus trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up, not, (as the Apoſtle adviſeth) <hi>in the nurture and admonition of the Lord,</hi> but in
<pb facs="tcp:169998:4"/> the ſuppoſals &amp; traditions of men, having little or no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance touching the reality of their Religion! Which ſome obſerving, and not having the happineſs to light upon the Truth, have quite abandoned all Piety whatſoever, thinking there is no firm ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to build the ſame. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent which miſchief in time to come, by bringing men to a certainty, (I mean ſuch men as own the Divine Authority of the Scripture) and withal to ſatisfie the juſt &amp; pious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of many, who would fain underſtand the truth of our religion, to the end they might
<pb facs="tcp:169998:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> not onely be built-up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, but alſo inſtruct their children and families in the ſame, I have here (according to the underſtanding I have gotten by continual meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the word of God) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled a Scripture-Catechiſm, wherein I bring the Reader to a ſure and certain knowledg of the chiefeſt things pertaining both to belief and practice, whilſt I my ſelf aſſert nothing, (as others have done before me) but onely introduce the Scripture faithfully uttering its own aſſertions, which all Chriſtians confeſs to be of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth. Take heed
<pb facs="tcp:169998:5"/> therefore whoſoever thou art, that lighteſt on this Book, and there readeſt things quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the doctrines that paſs currant amongſt the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſtians, (for I confeſs moſt of the things here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played, have ſuch a tendency) that thou fall not foul upon them, for thou canſt not do ſo without falling foul upon the holy Scripture it ſelf, inaſmuch as all the Anſwers throughout the whole Catechiſm are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſcribed out of it, and rightly applied to the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as thou thy ſelf maiſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if thou ſhalt make a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent inſpection into the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb facs="tcp:169998:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> texts with all their circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Thou wilt perhaps here reply, that the texts which I have cited, do indeed in the letter hold forth ſuch things as are contrary to the doctrines commonly received amongſt Chriſtians, but they ought to have a myſtical or figurative interpretation put upon them, and then both the doctrines and the texts of Scripture will ſuit well enough. To which I anſwer, that if we once take this liberty to impoſe our my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical or figurative interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Scripture, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expreſs warrant of the Scripture it ſelf, we ſhall have
<pb facs="tcp:169998:6"/> no ſetled belief, but be liable continually to be turned aſide by any one that can invent a new myſtical meaning of the Scripture, there being no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rule to judge of ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, as there is of the literal ones: nor is there any error, how abſurd and impious ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but may on ſuch terms be accorded with the Scripture. All the abominable Idolatries of the Papiſts, all the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Fopperies of the Turks, all the licentious Opinions and Practices of the Ranters, may by this means be not only pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liated, but defended by the Word of God. Certainly
<pb facs="tcp:169998:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> might we of our own heads figuratively interpret the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, when the letter is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repugnant to our ſenſes, nor to the ſcope of the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive texts, nor to a greater number of plain texts to the contrary, (for in ſuch caſes we muſt of neceſſity admit figures in the ſacred Volume, as well as we do in profane ones, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe both they and it will claſh either with themſelves, or with our ſenſes, which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it ſelf intimates to be of infallible certainty, ſee 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 2, 3.) might we, I ſay, at our pleaſure impoſe our Figures &amp; Allegories on the plain words
<pb facs="tcp:169998:7"/> of God, the Scripture would in very deed be, what ſome blaſphemouſly affirm it to be, <hi>a Noſe of wax.</hi> For inſtance, it is frequently aſſerted in the Scripture, that God hath a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude or ſhape, hath his place in the heavens, hath alſo affections or paſſions, as love, hatred, mercy, anger, and the like, neither is any thing to the contrary delivered there, unleſs ſeemingly in certain places, which neither for number, nor clearneſs are comparable unto thoſe of the other ſide. Why now ſhould I depart from the letter of the Scripture in theſe particulars, and boldly affirm
<pb facs="tcp:169998:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> with the generality of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, (or rather, with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of ſuch Chriſtians only, as being converſant with the falſe Philoſophy that reigneth in the Schools, have their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings perverted with wrong notions) that God is without a ſhape, in no certain place, and uncapable of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? Would not this be to uſe the Scripture like a noſe of wax, and when of it ſelf it looketh any way, to turn it aſide at our pleaſure? And would not God be ſo far from ſpeaking to our capacity in his Word, (which is the uſual Refuge of the Adverſaries,
<pb facs="tcp:169998:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:169998:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:169998:9"/> when in theſe and the like matters concerning God, they are preſſed with the plain words of the Scripture) as that he would by ſo doing render us altogether uncapable of finding out his meaning, whilſt he ſpake one thing, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the clean contrary? Yea, would he not have taken the direct courſe to make men ſubſtitute an Idol in his ſtead, (for the Adverſaries hold, that to conceive of God as having a ſhape, or affections, or being in a certain place, is Idolatry) if he deſcribed himſelf in the Scripture otherwiſe then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he is, without telling us
<pb facs="tcp:169998:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo much in plain terms, that we might not conceive amiſs of him? Thus we ſee, that when ſleep, which plainly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth weakneſs, and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, had been aſcribed to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. 23. the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is ſaid of him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121. 4. Again, when wearineſs had been attributed to him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 14. the ſame is expreſly denied of him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 28. And would not God (think ye) have done the like in thoſe forementioned things, were the caſe the ſame in them, as in the others? This conſideration is ſo preſſing, that a certain Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, (otherwiſe a very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:169998:10"/> and intelligent man) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the weight thereof, and not knowing how to avoid the ſame, took up (though ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unluckily) one erroneous tenet to maintain another, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us in a late book of his, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>Conjectura Caballiſtica, that for Moſes, by occaſion of his writings, to let the Jews entertain a conceit of God as in humane ſhape, was not any more a way to bring them into Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, then by acknowledging man to be God, as</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion does in Christ.</hi> How can this conſiſt even with conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy to his own Principles, whilſt he holds it to be falſe
<pb facs="tcp:169998:10"/> that God hath any ſhape, but true that Chriſt is God? For will a falſe opinion of God no ſooner lead men into Idolatry, then a true opinion of Chriſt? But it is no marvel that this Author, &amp; other learned men with him, entertain ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of God and Chriſt, as are repugnant to the current of the Scripture, whilſt they ſet ſo high a rate on the ſublime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but uncertain notions of the Platoniſts, and in the mean time ſlight the plain, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain letter of the ſacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as being far below the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, and written on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to comply with the rude
<pb facs="tcp:169998:11"/> apprehenſions of the vulgar, unleſs by a myſtical Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation they be ſcrued up to Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toniſm. This is the ſtone at which the Pride of learned men hath cauſed them continually to ſtumble, namely, to think that they can ſpeak more wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worthily of God, then he hath ſpoken of himſelf in his Word. This hath brought that more-then-Babyloniſh confuſion of language into the Chriſtian Religion, whilſt men have framed thoſe horrid and intricate expreſſions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of detecting and excluding Hereſies, but in truth to put a baffle on the
<pb facs="tcp:169998:11"/> ſimplicity of the Scripture, and uſher-in Hereſies, that ſo they might the more eaſily carry on their worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, which could not be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected but through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the people, nor the people brought into igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but by wrapping up Religion in ſuch monſtrous terms, as neither the people, nor they themſelves that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented them, (or at leaſt took them from the invention of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) did underſtand. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no poſſibility to reduce the Chriſtian Religion to its primitive integrity, (a thing, though much pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:169998:12"/> yea boaſted-of in Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, yet never hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſincerely endeavoured, much leſs effected, in that men have by ſevere penalties been hindered to reform Religion beyond ſuch a ſtint, as that of <hi>Luther,</hi> or at moſt that of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin)</hi> but by caſhiering thoſe many intricate terms, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed forms of ſpeaking, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on our Religion, and by wholly betaking our ſelvs to the plainneſs of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. For I have long ſince obſerved, (and finde my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to be true and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) that when to expreſs matters of religion men make
<pb facs="tcp:169998:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> uſe of words and phraſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of in the Scripture, they ſlily under them couch falſe doctrines, and obtrude them on us: for without queſtion the doctrines of the Scripture can be ſo aptly explained in no language as that of the Scripture it ſelf. Examine therefore the expreſſions <hi>of Gods being infinite and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, of his being a ſimple Act, of his ſubſiſting in three perſons, or after a threefold maner, of a Divine Circuminceſsion, of an Eternal Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, of an Eternal Proceſsion, of an Incarnation, of an Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Union, of a Communication of Properties, of the Mother of God,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169998:13"/> 
               <hi>of God dying, of God made man, of Tranſubſtantiation, of Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, of Original ſin, of Chriſts taking our nature on him, of Chriſts making ſatisfaction to God for our ſins, both paſt, preſent, and to come, of Chriſts fulfilling the Law for us, of Chriſts being puniſhed by God for us, of Chriſts merits, or his meritorious obedience both active and paſsive, of Chriſts purchaſing the kingdom of heaven for us, of Chriſts enduring the wrath of God, yea the pains of a damned man, of Chriſts riſing from the dead by his own power, of the Ubiquity of Chriſts body, of apprehending and applying Chriſts righteouſneſs to our ſelves by faith, of Chriſts being our</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169998:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Surety, of Chriſts paying our debts, of our ſins imputed to Chriſt, of Chriſts righteouſneſs imputed to us, of Chriſts dying to appeaſe the wrath of God, and reconcile him to us, of infuſed grace, of free grace, of the the world of the elect, of irreſiſtable workings of the Spirit in bringing men to believe, of carnal reaſon, of ſpiritual deſertions, of ſpiritual incomes, of the Outgoings of God, of taking up the Ordinance,</hi> &amp;c. and thou ſhalt finde, that as theſe forms of ſpeech are not owned by the Scripture, ſo neither the things contained in them. How excellent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was that advice of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle
<pb facs="tcp:169998:14"/> to him, chap. 1. 13. <hi>Hold fast the form of ſound words which thou hast heard of me, in faith and love which is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?</hi> for if we once let go thoſe forms of ſound words learned from the Apoſtles, and take up ſuch as have been coined by others in ſucceeding Ages, we ſhall together part with the Apoſtles doctrine, as wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience hath taught us. For after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great together with the Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> had once deviated from the language of the Scripture in the buſineſs touching the Son of God, calling him <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential</hi> with the Father, this
<pb facs="tcp:169998:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> opened a gap for others after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, under a pretence of guarding the Truth from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, to deviſe new terms at pleaſure, which did by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſo vitiate the chaſtity and ſimplicity of our Faith delivered in the Scripture, that there hardly remained ſo much as one point thereof ſound and entire. So that as it was wont to be diſputed in the Schools, whether the old ſhip of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> (which had in a maner been wholly altered at ſundry times by the acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of new pieces of timber upon the decay of the old) were the ſame ſhip it had been
<pb facs="tcp:169998:15"/> at firſt, and not rather another by degrees ſubſtituted in the ſtead thereof: in like maner there was ſo much of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive truth worn away by the corruption that did by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little overſpread the generality of Chriſtians, and ſo many errors in ſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of tacked to our Religion at ſeveral times, that one might juſtly queſtion whether it were the ſame Religion with that which Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles taught, and not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſince deviſed by men, and put in the room thereof. But thanks be to God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who amidſt
<pb facs="tcp:169998:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> the univerſal corruption of our Religion, hath preſerved his written Word entire, (for had men corrupted it, they would have made it ſpeak more favourably in behalf of their luſts and worldly inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, then it doth) which Word if we with diligence and ſincerity pry into, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to embrace the doctrine that is there plainly delivered, though all the world ſhould ſet it ſelf againſt us for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we ſhall eaſily diſcern the Truth, and ſo be enabled to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce our Religion to its firſt principles. For thus much I perceive by mine own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb facs="tcp:169998:16"/> who being otherwiſe of no great abilities, yet ſetting my ſelf with the aforeſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution for ſundry yeers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether upon an impartial ſearch of the Scripture, have not onely detected many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but here preſented the Readers with a body of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, exactly tranſcribed out of the Word of God; which body whoſoever ſhall well ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and digeſt in his mind, may by the ſame method, wherein I have gond before him, make a further enquiry into the Oracles of God, and draw forth whatſoever yet lies hid, and being brought to light
<pb facs="tcp:169998:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> will tend to the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Godlineſs amongſt us, for at this only all the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture aimeth: I ſay, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which all men, who have thorowly ſtudied the ſame, muſt of neceſſity be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured with, as breathing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the meer wiſdom of God, and being the exacteſt Rule of a holy life, (which all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions whatſoever confeſs to be the way unto Happineſs) that can be imagined, and whoſe Divinity will never even to the worlds end be queſtioned by any, but ſuch as are unwilling to deny their worldly luſts, and obey the
<pb facs="tcp:169998:17"/> pure and perfect precepts thereof. Which obedience whoſoever ſhall perform, he ſhall not onely in the life to come, but even in this life be equal unto Angels.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN BIDDLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:169998:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. OF the holy Scripture, or Word of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. Of the Creation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. Of Chriſt Jeſus.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. Of the Holy Ghoſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Of Salvation by Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. Of Chriſts Mediation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. Of Chriſts Prophetick Office.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. Of Remiſſion of Sins by Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. Of Chriſts Kingly Office.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. Of Chriſts Prieſtly Office.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. Of Chriſts death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. Of the Univerſality of Gods love.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. Of Chriſts Reſurection.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169998:18"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. Of Juſtification and Faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. Of keeping the Commandments, and having an eye to the Reward; of Perfection in vertue and godlineſs to be attained; and of departing from righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. Of the duty of Subjects and Magiſtrates, Wives and Husbands, Children and Parents, Servants and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. Of the behaviour of Men and Women in general; and in ſpecial of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Men, Aged Women, Young Women, and Young Men.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 19. Of Prayer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 20. Of the Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 21. Of the Government and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. Of Baptiſm.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. Of the Lords Supper.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 24. Of the Reſurrection of the dead, and the laſt Judgement; and what ſhall be the Final Condition of the Righteous and the Wicked thereupon.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169998:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Scripture-Catechiſm.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the holy Scripture, or Word of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſtion.</hi> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat doth the Scripture teſtifie concerning its own authority?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> All Scripture is given by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of God. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What, concerning its own uſefulneſs and excollencie?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All Scripture is profitable for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for reproof, for correction, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in righteouſneſs:</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169998:19"/>
                  <p>That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>The Law of the Lord is perfect, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the ſoul.</p>
                  <p>The Statutes of the Lord are right, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing the heart: the commandment of the Lord is pure, enlightning the eyes.</p>
                  <p>The judgements of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.</p>
                  <p>More to be deſired are they then gold, yea then much finde gold: ſweeter alſo then honey, and the honey-comb.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, by them is thy ſervant war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and in keeping of them there is great reward. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>The words of the Lord are pure words: as ſilver tried in a furnace of earth, purified ſeven times. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. 6.</p>
                  <p>Thy teſtimonies are wonderful, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth my ſoul keep them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 129.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What doth the Scripture teſtifie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning its own ſufficiencie?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The holy Scriptures are able to make wiſe unto ſalvation, through faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are written, that ye might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169998:19"/> that Jeſus is the Chriſt the Son of God, and that believing ye might have life through his name. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How would you anſwer them, who (notwithſtanding the teſtimony of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it ſelf touching its own ſufficiencie) ſhould bear you in hand, that certain tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and commandments of men are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Ye have made the commandment of God of none effect by your tradition.</p>
                  <p>In vain do they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 6, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What would you ſay to a man intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing a new form of words unheard-of in the Scripture, and ſuch a doctrine as tendeth not to godlineſs?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Hold faſt the form of ſound words which thou haſt heard, in faith and love which is in Chriſt Jeſus. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
                  <p>If any man teach otherwiſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not to <hi>wholeſom words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is according to godlineſs,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about queſtions and ſtrifes of words. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 3, 4.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169998:20"/>
                  <p>Let that abide in you, <hi>which ye have heard from the beginning.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What benefit ſhall redound unto us thereby?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If that which ye have heard from the beginning, ſhall remain in you, ye alſo ſhall continue in the Son, and in the Father. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What would you ſay to ſuch as ſhould require you to follow the judgement of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councels, and Learned Divines, when you finde it not agreeable to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To the law, and to the teſtimony: if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is the Scripture plain enough to be underſtood, even by the ſimple?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, <hi>making wiſe the ſimple. Pſal.</hi> 19. 7.</p>
                  <p>The entrance of thy words giveth light, it giveth underſtanding <hi>to the ſimple. Pſal.</hi> 119. 130.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is the Word of God a dead letter of it ſelf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The word of God is <hi>quick and powerful,</hi> and ſharper then any two-edged
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169998:20"/> ſword, piercing even to the dividing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12.</p>
                  <p>The words that I ſpeak unto you, <hi>they are ſpirit, and they are life. Joh.</hi> 6. 63.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> But do the things recorded in the Word of God concern us?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoſoever</hi> heareth theſe ſayings of mine, and doth them, I will liken him to a wiſe man which built his houſe upon a rock. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Which are the moſt affectionate paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in all the Scripture, flowing from the mouth of one enamoured on the Word of God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I have rejoyced in the way of thy teſtimonies, as much as in all riches.</p>
                  <p>My ſoul breaketh for the longing that it hath unto thy judgements at all times.</p>
                  <p>O how I love thy law! it is my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169998:21"/> all the day.</p>
                  <p>How ſweet are thy words unto my taſte! yea, ſweeter then honey to my mouth.</p>
                  <p>I love thy commandments above gold, yea above fine gold.</p>
                  <p>I rejoyce at thy word, as one that findeth great ſpoil. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 14, 20, 97, 103, 127, 162.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> HOw many Gods of Chriſtians are there?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> One God. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Who is this one God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Father, of whom are all things. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is this one God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A ſpirit. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you more ample deſcriptions of God in the Scripture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He is the bleſſed and onely Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, the King of kings, and Lord of lords:</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:169998:21"/>
                  <p>Who onely hath immortality, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the light which no man can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto; whom no man hath ſeen, nor can ſee. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>The Lord is gracious, and full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion: flow to anger, and of great mercy.</p>
                  <p>The Lord is good to all: and his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies are over all his works. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 8, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is not God, according to the current of the Scripture, in a certain place, namely heaven?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our God <hi>is in the heavens. Pſal.</hi> 115. 3.</p>
                  <p>The Lord looketh <hi>from heaven:</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth all the ſons of men.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>the place of his habitation</hi> he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon all the inhabitants of the earth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. 13, 14.</p>
                  <p>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be haſtie to utter any thing before God: for <hi>God is in heaven, and thou upon earth. Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 2.</p>
                  <p>Look down <hi>from thy habitation, from heaven,</hi> and bleſs thy people Iſrael. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26. 15.</p>
                  <p>Look down <hi>from heaven,</hi> and behold
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169998:22"/> 
                     <hi>from the habitation of thy holineſs, and of thy glory. Iſa.</hi> 63. 15.</p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from thy dwelling-place, from heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from the heavens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from heaven thy dwelling-place.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from the heavens, even from thy dwelling-place.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from the heavens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear thou <hi>from the heavens, even from thy dwelling-place.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. 21, 23, 25, 27, 30, 33, 35, 39.</p>
                  <p>Your Father <hi>which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your Father <hi>which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your Father <hi>which is in heaven. Mat.</hi> 5. 16, 45, 48.</p>
                  <p>Your Father <hi>which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Father <hi>which art in heaven. Mat.</hi> 6. 2, 9.</p>
                  <p>Your Father <hi>which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Father <hi>which is in heaven. Mat.</hi> 7. 11, 21.</p>
                  <p>In heaven their angels do always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the face of <hi>my Father which is in heaven. Matth.</hi> 18. 10.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:169998:22"/>
                  <p>Theſe words ſpake Jeſus, and lift up his eyes to <hi>heaven,</hi> and ſaid, Father, the hour is come, glorifie thy Son, that thy Son alſo may glorifie thee.</p>
                  <p>I have glorified thee on the earth.</p>
                  <p>And now, O Father, glorifie thou me with thine own ſelf. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 1, 4, 5.</p>
                  <p>I came forth from the Father, and am come into the world: again, <hi>I leave the world, and go to the Father. Joh.</hi> 16. 28.</p>
                  <p>Jeſus knew that his hour was come, <hi>that he ſhould depart out of this world to the Father. Joh.</hi> 13. 1.</p>
                  <p>And he being full of the holy Ghoſt, looked up ſtedfaſtly <hi>into heaven, and ſaw the glory of God, and Jeſus ſtanding on the right hand of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſaid, Behold, <hi>I ſee the heavens opened, and the Son of man ſtanding on the right hand of God. Act.</hi> 7. 55, 56.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is God in the Scripture ſaid to have any likeneſs, image, ſimilitude, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſhape?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God ſaid, Let us make man <hi>in our image, after our likeneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So God created man <hi>in his own image, in the image of God</hi> created he him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26, 27.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169998:23"/>
                  <p>In the day that God created man, in <hi>the likeneſs of God</hi> made he him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
                  <p>Whoſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed: for <hi>in the image of God</hi> made he man. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 6.</p>
                  <p>My ſervant Moſes is not ſo, who is faithful in all my houſe.</p>
                  <p>With him will I ſpeak mouth to mouth, even apparently, &amp; not in dark ſpeeches: and <hi>the ſimilitude of the Lord</hi> ſhall he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. <hi>Num.</hi> 12. 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>Therewith bleſs we God, even the Father: and therewith curſe we men, which are made after <hi>the ſimilitude of God. Jam.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
                  <p>Will ye ſpeak wickedly for God, and talk deceitfully for him?</p>
                  <p>Will ye accept <hi>his perſon? Job</hi> 13. 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>The Father himſelf, which hath ſent me, hath born witneſs of me. Ye have neither heard his voice at any time, nor ſeen <hi>his ſhape. Joh.</hi> 5. 37.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What paſſage of the Scripture inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, not onely that the Saints, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtate of the world to come, ſhall ſee God face to face, but alſo comprehend, or fully know him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When that which is perfect, is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169998:23"/> come, then that which is in part, ſhall be done away.</p>
                  <p>For now we ſee through a glaſs dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but then <hi>face to face:</hi> now I know in part, but then ſhall I know <hi>even as alſo I am known.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 10, 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Are there not, according to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual tenour of the Scripture, affections, or paſſions in God, as anger, fury, zeal, wrath, love, hatred, mercy, grace, jealouſie, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, grief, joy, fear?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Iſrael joyned himſelf to Baal-peor: and the <hi>anger of the Lord</hi> was kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, Take all the heads of the people, and hang them up before the Lord againſt the ſun, that <hi>the fierce anger of the Lord</hi> may be turned away. <hi>Num.</hi> 25. 3, 4.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſhall <hi>mine anger</hi> be accompliſhed, and I will cauſe <hi>my fury</hi> to reſt upon them, and I will be comforted: and they ſhall know that I the Lord have ſpoken it in <hi>my zeal,</hi> when I have accompliſhed <hi>my fury</hi> in them. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
                  <p>Moſes beſought the Lord his God, and ſaid, Lord, why doth <hi>thy wrath</hi> wax hot againſt thy people?</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:169998:24"/>
                  <p>Turn from <hi>thy fierce wrath. Exod.</hi> 32. 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The wrath of God</hi> is revealed from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt all ungodlineſs, and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The God of love</hi> and peace ſhall be with you. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 11.</p>
                  <p>He that loveth not, knoweth not God, for <hi>God is love.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God is love,</hi> and he that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in God, and God in him. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 8, 16.</p>
                  <p>Thou art not a God that hath pleaſure in wickedneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou hateſt</hi> all the workers of iniquity. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 4, 5.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed be God even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>the Father of mercies,</hi> and the God of all comfort. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
                  <p>God <hi>who is rich in mercy. Eph.</hi> 2. 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The God of all grace.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 10.</p>
                  <p>The Lord God, <hi>merciful and gracious. Exod.</hi> 34. 6.</p>
                  <p>I the Lord thy God, <hi>am ajealous God. Exod.</hi> 20. 5.</p>
                  <p>They have moved me <hi>to jealouſie</hi> with that which is not God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 21.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:169998:24"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord repented</hi> of the evil which he thought to do unto his people. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 14.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>it repented the Lord</hi> that he had made man on the earth, and <hi>it grieved him at his heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſaid, I will deſtroy man whom I have created, from the face of the earth, both man and beaſt, and the creeping thing, and the fowls of the air: for <hi>it repenteth me</hi> that I have made them. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>And they put away the ſtrange Gods from among them, and ſerved the Lord, and <hi>his ſoul was grieved</hi> for the miſery of Iſrael. <hi>Judg.</hi> 10. 16.</p>
                  <p>The Lord will again <hi>rejoyce</hi> over thee for good, as he <hi>rejoyced</hi> over thy fathers. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 9.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid, I would ſcatter them into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, I would make the remembrance of them to ceaſe from among men:</p>
                  <p>Were it not that <hi>I feared</hi> the wrath of the enemy, leſt their adverſaries ſhould behave themſelves ſtrangely, and leſt they ſhould ſay, Our hand is high, and the Lord hath not done all this. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 26, 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not God know all our thoughts, words and actions?</head>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:169998:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thou knoweſt my down-ſitting, and mine up-riſing; thou underſtandeſt my thought afar off.</p>
                  <p>Thou compaſſeſt my path, and my ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down, and art acquainted with all my ways.</p>
                  <p>For there is not a word in my tongue, but lo, O Lord, thou knoweſt it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 2, 3, 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> As for our free actions, which are neither paſt, nor preſent, but may afterwards either be or not be, what are the chief paſſages of the Scripture, from whence it is wont to be gathered, that God knoweth not ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, till they come to paſs? yea, that there are ſuch actions?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Out of the ground the Lord God formed every beaſt of the field, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fowl of the air, and brought them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Adam, <hi>to ſee what he would call them. Gen.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
                  <p>The Lord God ſaid, Behold, the man is become as one of us, to know good and evil: and now <hi>leſt he put forth his hand,</hi> and take alſo of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever;</p>
                  <p>Therefore the Lord God ſent him forth from the garden of Eden. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 22, 23.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169998:25"/>
                  <p>And God ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great in the earth, and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry imagination of the thoughts of his heart was onely evil continually.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And it repented the Lord that he had made man, and it grieved him at his heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſaid, I will deſtroy man, whom I have created, from the face of the earth, both man and beaſt, and the creeping thing, and the fowls of the air: for <hi>it repenteth me that I have made them. Gen.</hi> 6. 5, 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>And it came to paſs that <hi>God did tempt Abraham,</hi> and ſaid unto him,</p>
                  <p>Take now thy ſon, thine onely ſon Iſaac, and offer him for a burnt-offering.</p>
                  <p>And Abraham ſtretched forth his hand, and took the knife to ſlay his ſon.</p>
                  <p>And the angel of the Lord called unto him, and ſaid, Lay not thine hand upon the lad, neither do thou any thing unto him: for <hi>now I know that thou feareſt God, ſeeing thou haſt not withheld thy ſon, thine onely ſon, from me. Gen.</hi> 22. 1, 2, 10, 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>And God ſaid unto Moſes, Go and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the elders of Iſrael together, and ſay unto them, The Lord God of your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169998:26"/> fathers appeared unto me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they ſhall hearken to thy voice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Moſes anſwered, and ſaid, But behold, <hi>they will not believe me; nor hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my voice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſaid unto him, What is that in thy hand? And he ſaid, A rod.</p>
                  <p>And he ſaid, Caſt it on the ground. And he caſt it on the ground, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a ſerpent.</p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſaid to Moſes, Put forth thine hand, and take it by the tail. And he put forth his hand, and caught it, and it became a rod in his hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That they may believe that the Lord God of their fathers hath appeared to thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſaid furthermore unto him, Put now thine hand into thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. And he put his hand into his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: and when he took it out, behold, his hand was leprous as ſnow.</p>
                  <p>And he ſaid, Put thine hand into thy boſome again. And he put his hand into his boſome again, and plucked it out of his boſome, and behold, it was turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as his other fleſh.</p>
                  <p>And it ſhall come to paſs, <hi>if they will not believe thee, nor hearken to the voice of</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169998:26"/> 
                     <hi>the firſt ſigne, that they will believe the voice of the latter ſigne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And it ſhall come to paſs, <hi>if they will not believe alſo theſe two ſignes, neither hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to thy voice,</hi> that thou ſhalt take of the water of the river, and pour it upon the dry-land: and the water, which thou takeſt out of the river, ſhall become blood upon the dry-land. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 15, 16, 18. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>And it came to paſs, when Pharaoh had let the people go, God led them not thorow the way of the land of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims, although that was neer: for God ſaid, <hi>Leſt peradventure the people repent when they ſee war, and they return to Egypt. Exod.</hi> 13. 17.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid the Lord unto Moſes, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I will rain bread from heaven for you; and the people ſhall go out, and gather a certain rate every day, <hi>that I may prove them, whether they will walk in my law, or no. Exod.</hi> 16. 4.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>the Lord repented of the evil which he thought to do unto his people. Exod.</hi> 32. 14.</p>
                  <p>I have heard the murmurings of the children of Iſrael, which they murmur againſt me.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169998:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doubtleſs ye ſhall not come into the land concerning which I ſware to make you dwell therein.</hi> Num. 14. 27, 30.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt remember all the way which the Lord thy God led thee theſe fourty yeers in the wilderneſs, to humble thee, and <hi>to prove thee, to know what was in thy heart, whether thou wouldſt keep his commandments, or no. Deut.</hi> 8. 2.</p>
                  <p>The Lord your God <hi>proveth you, to know whether ye love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your ſoul. Deut.</hi> 13. 3.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid, I would ſcatter them into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, I would make the remembrance of them to ceaſe from among men:</p>
                  <p>Were it not that <hi>I feared the wrath of the enemy, leſt their adverſaries ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves ſtrangely; leſt they ſhould ſay,</hi> Our hand is high, and the Lord hath not done all this. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Now theſe are the nations which the Lord left, <hi>to prove Iſrael by them; and they were to prove Iſrael by them, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would hearken unto the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord. Judg.</hi> 3. 1, 4.</p>
                  <p>The Lord God of Iſrael ſaith, <hi>I ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that thy houſe, and the houſe of thy</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169998:27"/> 
                     <hi>father, ſhould walk before me for ever: but now the Lord ſaith, Be it far from me:</hi> for them that honour me, I will honour; and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 30.</p>
                  <p>Then came the word of the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Samuel, ſaying, <hi>It repenteth me that I have ſet up Saul to be king, for he is turned back from following me, and hath not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my commandments.</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>Hezekiah proſpered in all his works.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit in the buſineſs of the ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of the princes of Babylon, who ſent unto him to enquire of the wonder that was done in the land, God left him, <hi>to try him, that he might know what was in his heart.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32. 31.</p>
                  <p>What could have been done more to my vineyard, that I have not done in it? <hi>wherefore, when I looked that it ſhould bring forth grapes, brought it forth wilde grapes? Iſa.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſaith the Lord, Stand in the court of the Lords houſe, and ſpeak unto all the cities of Judah;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If ſo be they will hearken, and turn every man from his evil way, that I may repent me</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169998:28"/> 
                     <hi>of the evil which I purpoſe to do unto them. Jer.</hi> 26. 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>This word came unto Jeremiah from the Lord, ſaying,</p>
                  <p>Take thee a roll of a book, and write therein all the words, that I have ſpoken unto thee againſt Iſrael, and againſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may be that the houſe of Judah will hear all the evil which I purpoſe to do unto them, that they may return every man from his evil way, that I may forgive their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and their ſin. Jer.</hi> 36. 1, 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>The word of the Lord came to me, ſaying,</p>
                  <p>Prepare thee ſtuff for removing, and remove by day in their ſight; <hi>it may be they will conſider,</hi> though they be a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious houſe. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12. 1, 3.</p>
                  <p>In every thing by prayer and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with thankſgiving, <hi>let your requeſts be made known unto God. Phil.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
                  <p>As we were allowed of God to be put in truſt with the Goſpel, ſo we ſpeak, not as pleaſing men, but God, <hi>which try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our hearts.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How muſt we worſhip God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They that worſhip him, muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169998:28"/> him in ſpirit and truth. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How muſt one love him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy might. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Could we love him <hi>with all the heart,</hi> if he were <hi>three?</hi> or is his <hi>oneneſs</hi> the cauſe hinted by Moſes why we ſhould love him thus? How ſound the words ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s Tranſlation</note> truth of the Hebrew text?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Hear, O Iſrael, the Lord our God, the Lord <hi>is one. Deut.</hi> 6. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein conſiſteth the love of God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This is the love of God, <hi>that we keep his commandments.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoſo keepeth his word, in him</hi> verily is the love of God perfected. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What if a man ſay he loveth God, and in the mean time hateth his brother?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If a man ſay, I love God, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his brother, he is a lyer: for he that loveth not his brother, whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God, whom he hath not ſeen? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What advantage will it be to you, to know the Father the onely true God? How ſpeaketh Chriſt in his prayer to the Father, concerning this thing?</head>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169998:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This is life eternal, that they may know thee the onely true God. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 3.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Creation.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WEre the heaven and earth from all eternity, or created at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time? and by whom?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In the beginning God created heaven and earth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How long was God a making them?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In ſix days the Lord made heaven and earth, the ſea, and all that in them is. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How did God create man?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord God formed man of the duſt of the ground, and breathed into his noſtrils the breath of life; and man became a living ſoul. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How did he create woman?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord cauſed a deep ſleep to fall upon Adam, and he ſlept; and he took one of his ribs, and cloſed up the fleſh in ſtead thereof.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:169998:29"/>
                  <p>And the rib, which the Lord God had taken from man, made he a woman, and brought her unto the man. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 21, 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Why was ſhe called <hi>woman?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe ſhe was taken out of man. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What doth Moſes infer from her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a woman, and brought unto the man?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Therefore ſhall a man leave his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his mother, and ſhall cleave to his wife: and they ſhall be one fleſh. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Where did God put man, after he was created?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord God planted a garden eaſtward in Eden, and <hi>there</hi> he put the man whom he had formed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What commandment gave he to the man, when he put him into the garden?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord God commanded the man, ſaying, Of every tree of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thou maiſt freely eat:</p>
                  <p>But of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou ſhalt not eat of it; for in the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 16, 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Was the man deceived to eat of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169998:30"/> forbidden fruit?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Adam was not deceived, but the woman being deceived was in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> By whom was the woman deceived?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The ſerpent beguiled Eve through his ſubtilty. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How was the woman induced to eat of the forbidden fruit? and how, the man?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the woman ſaw that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleaſant to the eyes, and a tree to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to make one wiſe, ſhe took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave alſo to her husband with her, and he did eat. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What effect followed upon their eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The eyes of them both were ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and they knew that they were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: and they ſewed fig-leaves together, and made themſelves aprons. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did the ſin of our firſt parents in eating of the forbidden fruit bring both upon them and their poſterity the guilt of hell-fire, deface the image of God in them, darken their underſtanding, enſlave their will, deprive them of power to do good, and cauſe mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169998:30"/> If not, what are the true penalties that God denounced againſt them for the ſaid of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Unto the woman he ſaid, I will greatly multiply thy ſorrow, and thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: in ſorrow thou ſhalt bring forth children; and thy deſire ſhall be to thy husband, and he ſhall rule over thee.</p>
                  <p>Unto Adam he ſaid, Becauſe thou haſt hearkened unto the voice of thy wife, and haſt eaten of the tree, of which I commanded thee, ſaying, Thou ſhalt not eat of it: curſed is the ground for thy ſake; in ſorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life.</p>
                  <p>Thorns alſo and thiſtles ſhall it bring forth to thee: and thou ſhalt eat the herb of the field.</p>
                  <p>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground: for out of it waſt thou taken; for duſt thou art, and unto duſt ſhalt thou return. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 16, 17, 18, 19.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:169998:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of Christ Jeſus.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> HOw many Lords of Chriſtians are there, by way of diſtinction from that one God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> One Lord. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Who is that one Lord?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How was Jeſus Chriſt born?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The birth of Jeſus Chriſt was on this wiſe: when as his mother Mary was eſpouſed to Joſeph, before they came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhe was found with childe of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
                  <p>The angel ſaid unto her, Fear not, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</p>
                  <p>Behold, thou ſhalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a ſon, and ſhalt call his name Jeſus.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall be great, and ſhall be called the Son of the Higheſt.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid Mary to the angel, How ſhall this be, ſeeing I know not a man?</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169998:31"/>
                  <p>And the angel anſwered and ſaid unto her, The holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the power of the Higheſt ſhall overſhadow thee. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 30, 31, 32, 34, 35.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How came Jeſus Chriſt to be Lord, according to the opinion of the apoſtle Paul?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To this end Chriſt both died, and roſe, and revived, <hi>that he might be Lord of the dead and living.</hi> Rom. 14. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith the apoſtle Peter alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the time and maner of his being made Lord?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Jeſus hath God raiſed up, whereof we are all witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>Therefore being by the right hand of God exalted, and having received of the Father the promiſe of the holy Ghoſt, he hath ſhed forth this, which ye now ſee and hear.</p>
                  <p>Therefore let all the houſe of Iſrael know aſſuredly, that <hi>God hath made that ſame Jeſus, whom ye crucified, both Lord and Chriſt.</hi> Acts 2. 32, 33, 36.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did not Jeſus approve himſelf to be God by his miracles? and did he not thoſe miracles by a <hi>Divine nature of his own, and becauſe he was God himſelf?</hi> What
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169998:32"/> is the determination of the Apoſtle Peter in this behalf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus of Nazareth, <hi>a man approved of God by miracles, wonders and ſignes, which God did by him. Acts</hi> 2. 22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God anointed Jeſus of Nazareth with the holy Ghoſt, and with power,</hi> who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppreſſed of the devil: <hi>for God was with him. Acts</hi> 10. 38.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Could not Chriſt do all things of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? and was it not an eternal Son of God that took fleſh upon him, and to whom the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature of Chriſt was perſonally united, that wrought all his works? Anſwer me to theſe things in the words of the Son him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Verily, verily I ſay unto you, <hi>The Son can do nothing of himſelf, but what he ſeeth the Father do:</hi> for what things ſoever he doth, theſe alſo doth the Son like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                  <p>For the Father loveth the Son, and ſheweth him all things that himſelf doth; and he will ſhew him greater works then theſe, that ye may marvel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I can do nothing of my ſelf. Joh.</hi> 5. 19, 20, 30.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169998:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Father that dwelleth in me, he doth the works. Joh.</hi> 14. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What reaſon doth the Son ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, why the Father did not forſake him, and caſt him out of favour? was it not becauſe he was of the ſame eſſence with him, ſo that it was impoſſible for the Father to forſake him; or ceaſe to love him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. He that hath ſent me, is with me;</hi> the Father hath not left me alone, <hi>for I do always thoſe things that pleaſe him. Joh.</hi> 8. 28, 29.</p>
                  <p>As the Father hath loved me, ſo have I loved you: continue in my love.</p>
                  <p>If ye keep my commandments, ye ſhall abide in my love; <hi>even as I have kept my Fathers commandments, and abide in his love. Joh.</hi> 15. 9, 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth the Scripture avouch Chriſt to be the Son of God becauſe he was eternally begotten out of the Divine eſſence, or for other reaſons agreeing to him onely as a man? Rehearſe the paſſages to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The angel ſaid unto her, Fear not Mary: for thou haſt found favour with God.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169998:33"/>
                  <p>And behold, <hi>thou ſhalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a ſon, and ſhalt call his name Jeſus. He ſhall be great, and ſhall be called the Son of the Higheſt,</hi> and the Lord God ſhall give to him the throne of his father David.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid Mary unto the angel, How ſhall this be, ſeeing I know not a man?</p>
                  <p>And the angel anſwered and ſaid unto her, The holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the power of the Higheſt ſhall overſhadow thee: <hi>therefore alſo that holy thing which ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Son of God. Luke</hi> 1. 30, 31, 32, 34, 35.</p>
                  <p>Say ye of him, <hi>whom the Father hath ſanctified, and ſent into the world,</hi> Thou blaſphemeſt, becauſe I ſaid, <hi>I am the Son of God? Joh.</hi> 10. 36.</p>
                  <p>We declare unto you glad tidings, how that the promiſe which was made unto the fathers,</p>
                  <p>God hath fulfilled the ſame unto us their children, in that he hath raiſed up Jeſus again, as it is alſo written in the ſecond Pſalm, <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee. Act.</hi> 13. 32, 33.</p>
                  <p>And from Jeſus Chriſt, who is the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169998:33"/> faithful witneſs, and <hi>the firſt-begotten of the dead. Rev.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
                  <p>He is the head of the body, the Church: who is the beginning, <hi>the firſt-born from the dead. Col.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
                  <p>Being made ſo much better then the angels, <hi>As he hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent name then they.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For unto which of the angels ſaid he at any time, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee?</hi> And again, <hi>I will be to him a Father, and he ſhall be to me a Son.</hi> Heb. 1. 4, 5.</p>
                  <p>So alſo Chriſt glorified not himſelf, to be made an high-prieſt: but he that ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee. Heb.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
                  <p>Whom he did foreknow, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be <hi>the firſt-born among many brethren. Rom.</hi> 8. 29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith the Son himſelf concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the prerogative of God the Father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If ye loved me, ye would rejoyce, becauſe I ſaid, I go unto the Father: <hi>for my Father is greater then I. Joh.</hi> 14. 28.</p>
                  <p>But of that day and that hour knoweth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169998:34"/> none, no not the angels which are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>nor the Son, but the Father. Mark</hi> 13. 32.</p>
                  <p>Of that day and hour knoweth none, no not the angels of heaven, <hi>but my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther onely. Matth.</hi> 24. 36.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith the Apoſtle Paul?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Then cometh the end, <hi>when he ſhall have delivered up the kingdom to God even the Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And when all things ſhall be ſubdued unto him, then ſhall <hi>the Son alſo himſelf be ſubject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24, 28.</p>
                  <p>I would have you know, that the head of every man is Chriſt: and the head of the woman is the man: <hi>and the head of Chriſt is God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
                  <p>All are yours,</p>
                  <p>And ye are Chriſts, and <hi>Chriſt is Gods.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 22, 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Howbeit is not Chriſt dignified, as with the title of <hi>Lord,</hi> ſo alſo with that of <hi>God,</hi> in the Scripture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thomas anſwered and ſaid unto him, My Lord, and <hi>my God. John</hi> 20. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169998:34"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Was he ſo the God of Thomas, as that he himſelf in the mean time did not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge another to be his God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus ſaith unto her, Go to my brethren, and ſay unto them, I aſcend unto my Father, and your Father; and to <hi>my God,</hi> and your God. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 17.</p>
                  <p>Him that overcometh will I make a pillar in the temple of <hi>my God,</hi> and he ſhall go no more out: and I will write upon him the name of <hi>my God,</hi> and the name of the city of <hi>my God,</hi> which is new Jeruſalem, which cometh down out of heaven from <hi>my God. Rev.</hi> 3. 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you any paſſage of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, where Chriſt, at the ſame time that he hath the appellation of <hi>God</hi> given to him, is ſaid to have a God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> But unto the Son he ſaith, Thy throne, <hi>O God,</hi> is for ever and ever; a ſcepter of righteouſneſs is the ſcepter of thy kingdom:</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt loved righteouſneſs, and hated iniquity, wherefore <hi>God thy God</hi> hath anointed thee with the oyl of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs above thy fellows. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 8, 9.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:169998:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> HOw many Holy Spirits of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are there?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> One Spirit. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein conſiſts the prerogative of the Holy Spirit above other ſpirits?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God.</p>
                  <p>For who of men knoweth the things of a man, ſave the ſpirit of a man which is in him? even ſo <hi>the things of God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth none, ſave the Spirit of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 10, 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Whence is the Holy Ghoſt ſent?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Down from heaven. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> By whom?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. God ſent forth the Spirit of his Son</hi> into your hearts. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not Chriſt affirm that he alſo ſends him? how ſpeaketh he?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If I go not away, the Comforter will not come unto you: but if I depart, <hi>I will ſend him. Joh.</hi> 16. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:169998:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Had Jeſus Chriſt always the power to ſend the Holy Ghoſt, or did he obtain it at a certain time?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Jeſus hath God raiſed up, whereof we are all witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore being by the right hand of God exalted, and having received of the Father the promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt, he hath ſhed forth this, which ye now ſee and hear. Act.</hi> 2. 32, 33.</p>
                  <p>This ſpake he of the Spirit, which they that believe on him, ſhould receive: <hi>for the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Jeſus was not yet glorified. Joh.</hi> 7. 39.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What were the general benefits ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruing to Chriſtians by the Holy Ghoſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. By one Spirit are we all baptized into one body,</hi> whether we be Jews or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, whether we be bond or free; and have been all made <hi>to drink into one Spirit.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13.</p>
                  <p>The Spirit himſelf <hi>beareth witneſs with our ſpirit,</hi> that we are the children of God.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe the Spirit alſo <hi>helpeth our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities:</hi> for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought: but the Spirit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>maketh interceſſion for us</hi> with groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169998:36"/> which cannot be uttered.</p>
                  <p>And he that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the minde of the Spirit, becauſe <hi>he maketh interceſſion for the Saints</hi> according to the will of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 16, 26, 27.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The love of God</hi> is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt which is given unto us. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
                  <p>Your <hi>love</hi> in the Spirit. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 8.</p>
                  <p>That the God of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of glory, may give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you <hi>the ſpirit of wiſdom and revelation in the knowledge of him. Eph.</hi> 1. 17.</p>
                  <p>The God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound <hi>in hope</hi> through the power of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 13.</p>
                  <p>The kingdom of God is not meat and drink, but righteouſneſs and peace, <hi>and joy</hi> in the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17.</p>
                  <p>Then had the Churches reſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Judea, and Galilee, and Samaria, and were edified, and walking in the fear of the Lord, <hi>and in the comfort of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> were multiplied. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 31.</p>
                  <p>The he would grant you according to the riches of his glory, <hi>to be ſtrengthned</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:169998:36"/> 
                     <hi>with might, by his Spirit, in the inner man. Eph.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What are the ſpecial benefits accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the apoſtles by the holy Ghoſt? what ſaith Chriſt to them hereof?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Comforter, which is the holy Ghoſt, whom the Father will ſend in my name, <hi>he ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I have ſaid unto you. Joh.</hi> 15. 26.</p>
                  <p>When he, the Spirit of truth is come, <hi>he will guide you into all truth. Joh.</hi> 16. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Should the holy Ghoſt lead them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth, as ſpeaking of himſelf, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting of his own fulneſs? What ſaith Chriſt concerning him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf: but whatſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall glorifie me: for he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of mine, and ſhall ſhew it unto you. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 13, 14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Qu. <hi>Do men receive the holy Ghoſt</hi> while they are of the world, and in their natural condition, <hi>to the end that they</hi> may become the children of God, may receive the word, may believe, may repent, may obey Chriſt? <hi>or,</hi> after they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169998:37"/> are become the children of God, have received the word, do believe, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, do obey Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever.</p>
                  <p>Even the Spirit of truth, <hi>whom the world cannot receive,</hi> becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God,</hi> for they are fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto him: neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe ye are ſons,</hi> God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying, Abba, Father. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
                  <p>When the Apoſtles which were at Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, heard that Samaria <hi>had received the word of God,</hi> they ſent unto them Peter and John, who when they were come down, prayed for them <hi>that they might receive the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For as yet he was fallen upon none of them:</hi> onely they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 14, 15, 16.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:169998:37"/>
                  <p>He that believeth on me, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture hath ſaid, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water.</p>
                  <p>But this he ſpake of the Spirit, which they that believe on him <hi>ſhould receive: for the holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Jeſus was not yet glorified. Joh.</hi> 7. 38, 39.</p>
                  <p>Paul, having paſſed thorow the upper coaſts, came to Epheſus, and finding cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain diſciples,</p>
                  <p>He ſaid unto them, <hi>Have ye received the holy Ghoſt ſince ye believed?</hi> and they ſaid unto him, <hi>We have not ſo much as heard whether there be any holy Ghoſt, Act.</hi> 19. 1, 2.</p>
                  <p>In whom alſo, <hi>after that ye believed,</hi> ye were ſealed with the holy Spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
                  <p>That we might receive the promiſe of the Spirit <hi>through faith. Gal.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
                  <p>God made choice among us, that the Gentiles by my mouth ſhould hear the word of the Goſpel, and <hi>believe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And God which knoweth the hearts, <hi>bare them witneſs, giving them the holy Ghoſt,</hi> even as he did unto us. <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 7, 8.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169998:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repent</hi> and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſins, and <hi>ye ſhall receive the gift of the holy Ghoſt. Acts</hi> 2. 38.</p>
                  <p>And we are his witneſſes of theſe things, and ſo is alſo the holy Ghoſt, whom God hath given <hi>to them that obey him. Acts</hi> 5. 32.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Salvation by Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> IS not Chriſt in Scripture called a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our Lord and <hi>Saviour</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is Chriſt our Saviour originally and of himſelf, or becauſe he was given, exalted, and raiſed up by another to be a Saviour?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> There is no other name under heaven <hi>given</hi> among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 12.</p>
                  <p>Him hath God <hi>exalted to be a Prince and Saviour. Acts</hi> 5. 31.</p>
                  <p>Of this mans ſeed hath God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe, <hi>raiſed unto Iſrael</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:169998:38"/> 
                     <hi>a Saviour, Jeſus. Acts</hi> 13. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How do the Saints expect to be ſaved by Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We ſhall be ſaved by his life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 10.</p>
                  <p>We look for a <hi>Saviour,</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who ſhall change our vile bodies, that they may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body, according to the working whereby he is able even to ſubdue all things unto himſelf. Phil.</hi> 3. 20, 21.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Chriſts Mediation.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> IS not Chriſt called the Mediator between God and men?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> There is one God, and <hi>one Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor between God and men, the man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is not Chriſt alſo called the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the New Covenant? or of a better Covenant?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus the Mediator of the <hi>new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Heb.</hi> 12. 24.</p>
                  <p>He is the Mediator of a <hi>better covenant. Heb.</hi> 8. 6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169998:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Chriſts Prophetick Office.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> IS not Chriſt dignified as with the title of <hi>Mediator,</hi> ſo alſo with that of <hi>Prophet?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He ſhall ſend Jeſus Chriſt, which before was preached unto you.</p>
                  <p>For Moſes truly ſaid unto the fathers, <hi>A prophet</hi> ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, of your brethren, like unto me. <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 20, 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Foraſmuch as Chriſt was to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>like unto Moſes,</hi> and Moſes had this priviledge above other Prophets, that God made not himſelf known to him in a viſion, nor ſpake to him in a dream, but face to face, as a man ſpeaketh to a friend, and ſhewed to him the ſimilitude of the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 11. <hi>Num.</hi> 12. 6, 7, 8. can you cite any paſſage of the Scripture, which intimateth that Chriſt did ſee God, before the diſcharge of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Every man that hath heard and learned from the Father, cometh to me.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:169998:39"/>
                  <p>Not that any man hath ſeen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſave <hi>he which is from God, he hath ſeen the Father. Joh.</hi> 6. 45, 46.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> From whence doth it appear that Chriſt, like to Moſes, heard from God the things that he ſpake?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Ye ſeek to kill me, <hi>a man that hath told you the truth, which I have heard from God. Joh.</hi> 8. 40.</p>
                  <p>He that hath ſent me is true, and I ſpeak to the world thoſe things <hi>which I have heard from him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As my Father hath taught me,</hi> I ſpeak theſe things. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 26, 28.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All things that I have heard from my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> have I made known unto you. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 15.</p>
                  <p>I have given unto them the words <hi>which thou gaveſt me,</hi> and they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Can you further cite any paſſages to prove that Chriſt as a man aſcended into heaven, and was there, and came from God out of heaven, before he ſhewed himſelf to the world, and diſcharged his Prophetick Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; ſo that the talking of Moſes with God in the perſon of an angel bearing the name of God, was but a ſhadow of Chriſts talking with God?</head>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169998:40"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No man <hi>hath aſcended into heaven,</hi> but he that <hi>came down from heaven, the Son of man,</hi> which is <hi>(or, rather,</hi> was) in heaven. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
                  <p>What and if ye ſhall ſee <hi>the Son of man</hi> aſcending up where <hi>he was before? Joh.</hi> 6. 62.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I came down from heaven</hi> not to do mine own will, but the will of him that ſent me. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 38.</p>
                  <p>I am the living bread <hi>which came down from heaven. Joh.</hi> 6. 51.</p>
                  <p>Moſes gave you not that bread from heaven, but my Father giveth you <hi>the true bread from heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the bread of God is <hi>he which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down from heaven,</hi> and giveth life to the world.</p>
                  <p>The Jews then murmured at him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaid, I am the bread <hi>which came down from heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And they ſaid, Is not this Jeſus the ſon of Joſeph, whoſe father and mother we know? how is it then that he ſaith, <hi>I came down from heaven? Joh.</hi> 6. 32, 33, 41, 42.</p>
                  <p>As the living Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Father: ſo, he that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169998:40"/> eateth me, ſhall live by me.</p>
                  <p>This is that bread <hi>which came down from heaven. Joh.</hi> 6. 57, 58.</p>
                  <p>I proceeded forth and <hi>came from God. Ioh.</hi> 8. 42.</p>
                  <p>Ye are from beneath, <hi>I am from above:</hi> ye are of this world, I am not of this world. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 29.</p>
                  <p>Jeſus knowing that <hi>he was come from God,</hi> and goeth to God. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 1, 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I came forth from the Father,</hi> and am come into the world: again, I leave the world, and go to the Father.</p>
                  <p>His diſciples ſaid unto him, Lo, now thou ſpeakeſt plainly, and ſpeakeſt no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
                  <p>Now are we ſure that thou knoweſt all things, and needeſt not that any man ſhould ask thee: by this we believe that thou <hi>cameſt forth from God. Ioh.</hi> 16. 28, 29, 30.</p>
                  <p>I have given unto them the words which thou gaveſt me, and they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them, <hi>and known ſurely that I came out from thee. Ioh.</hi> 17. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Of what conſequence was it, in the judgement of Chriſt himſelf, that his diſciples had believed that he came out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169998:41"/> from God? what ſaith he?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Father himſelf loveth you, becauſe ye have believed that I came out from God. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not Iohn the Baptiſt affirm that Chriſt ſurpaſſed all others, becauſe he came down from heaven above? what ſaith he?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. He that cometh from above, is above all:</hi> he that is of the earth, <hi>(or rather,</hi> was from the earth) is earthly, <hi>(or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> is of the earth) and ſpeaketh of the earth. <hi>He that cometh from heaven, is above all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what he hath ſeen and heard, that he ſpeaketh. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 30, 31, 32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> You have already ſhewed that Chriſt was like unto Moſes in ſeeing God, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him the things which he ſpake. But Moſes exceeded all other Prophets likewiſe in that he onely was a law-giver. Was Chriſt therefore like unto Moſes in giving a law alſo? and is there any mention of his law?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Bear ye one anothers burthens, and ſo fulfil <hi>the law of Chriſt. Gal.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
                  <p>Where is boaſting then? It is excluded. By what law? Of works? Nay: but <hi>by the law of faith. Rom.</hi> 3. 27.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169998:41"/>
                  <p>The law of liberty. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
                  <p>The perfect law of liberty. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not Chriſt then partly perfect, partly correct the law of Moſes? What is the determination of Christ himſelf concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Ye have heard, <hi>that it was ſaid to them of old time,</hi> Thou ſhalt not kill: and whoſoever ſhall kill, ſhall be in danger of the judgement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I ſay unto you,</hi> That whoſoever is angry with his brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the judgement: and whoſoever ſhall ſay unto his brother, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ka, ſhall be in danger of the councel: but whoſoever ſhall ſay, Thou fool, ſhall be in danger of hell-fire.</p>
                  <p>Ye have heard <hi>that it was ſaid to them of old time,</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I ſay unto you,</hi> That whoſoever looketh upon a woman to luſt after her, hath committed adultery with her alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in his heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It hath been ſaid,</hi> Whoſoever ſhall put away his wife, let him give her a writing of divorcement.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169998:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I ſay unto you,</hi> That whoſoever ſhall put away his wife, ſaving for the cauſe of fornication, cauſeth her to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultery: and whoſoever ſhall marry her that is divorced, committeth adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
                  <p>Again, ye have heard <hi>that it hath been ſaid to them of old time,</hi> Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thine oaths.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I ſay unto you,</hi> Swear not at all, neither by heaven, for it is Gods throne;</p>
                  <p>Nor by the earth, for it is his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool: neither by Jeruſalem, for it is the city of the great King.</p>
                  <p>Neither ſhalt thou ſwear by thy head, becauſe thou canſt not make one hair white or black.</p>
                  <p>But let your communication be, Yea, yea; nay, nay: for whatſoever is more then theſe, cometh of evil.</p>
                  <p>Ye have heard <hi>that it hath been ſaid,</hi> An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I ſay unto you,</hi> That ye reſiſt not evil: but whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on thy right cheek, turn to him the other alſo.</p>
                  <p>And if a man will ſue thee at the law,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169998:42"/> and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloke alſo.</p>
                  <p>And whoſoever ſhall compel thee to go a mile, go with him twain.</p>
                  <p>Give to him that asketh thee, and from him that would borrow of thee, turn not thou away.</p>
                  <p>Ye have heard <hi>that it hath been ſaid,</hi> Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour, and hath thine enemy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I ſay unto you,</hi> Love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you.</p>
                  <p>That ye may be the children of your Father which is in heaven: for he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ſun to riſe on the evil and on the good, and ſendeth rain on the juſt and on the unjuſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 21, 22, 27, 28, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> You have made it plainly to appear that the law of faith, or the new covenant, whereof Chriſt was the Mediator, is better then the law of works, or the old covenant, whereof Moſes was the Mediator, in reſpect of precepts: is it alſo better in reſpect of promiſes?</head>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169998:43"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He hath obtained a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent miniſtry, by how much he is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of <hi>a better covenant, which was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed upon better promiſes. Heb.</hi> 8. 6.</p>
                  <p>The law made nothing perfect, but <hi>the bringing in of a better hope</hi> did. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Were thoſe better promiſes of God touching eternal life and immortality hidden in the dark, and not brought to light under the law?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus hath brought <hi>life and immortality</hi> to light through the Goſpel. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Though the promiſes of the Goſpel be better then thoſe of the law, yet are they not (as well as thoſe of the law) propoſed under conditions of faith and perſeverance therein, of holineſs and obedience, of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, of ſuffering for Chriſt and his truth, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> How ſpeaketh the Scripture here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As Moſes lifted up the ſerpent in the wilderneſs; even ſo muſt the Son of man be lifted up:</p>
                  <p>That <hi>whoſoever believeth in him,</hi> ſhould not periſh, but have eternal life.</p>
                  <p>For God ſo loved the World, that he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169998:43"/> gave his onely begotten Son, that <hi>whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever believeth in him,</hi> ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that believeth on him,</hi> is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: but <hi>he that believeth not,</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already, <hi>becauſe he hath not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the name of the onely-begotten Son of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that believeth on the Son,</hi> hath ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life: and <hi>he that believeth not the Son,</hi> ſhall not ſee life: but the wrath of God abideth on him. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 14, 15, 16, 18, 36.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid Jeſus to the Jews that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on him, <hi>If ye continue in my word,</hi> then are ye my diſciples indeed. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 31.</p>
                  <p>We are made partakers of Chriſt, <hi>if we hold the beginning of our confidence ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt to the end. Heb.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
                  <p>But Chriſt as a Son over his own houſe; whoſe houſe we are, <hi>If we hold faſt the confidence, and the rejoyoing of the hope firm unto the end. Heb.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If a man purge himſelf from theſe, he ſhall be a veſſel unto honour.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If ye live after the fleſh,</hi> ye ſhall die: but <hi>if ye through the Spirit mortifie the deeds of</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:169998:44"/> 
                     <hi>the body,</hi> ye ſhall live. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repent ye therefore, and be converted,</hi> that your ſins may be blotted out. <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 19.</p>
                  <p>Remember from whence thou art fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and repent, and do the firſt works, <hi>or elſe I will come unto thee quickly,</hi> and will remove thy candleſtick out of his place, <hi>except thou repent. Rev.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
                  <p>Repent, <hi>or elſe I will come unto thee quickly,</hi> and will fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 16.</p>
                  <p>If ye know theſe things, happie are ye <hi>if ye do them. Joh.</hi> 13. 17.</p>
                  <p>Whoſoever cometh to me, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my ſayings, <hi>and doth them,</hi> I will ſhew you to whom he is like.</p>
                  <p>He is like a man which built a houſe, and digged deep, and laid the foundation on a rock.</p>
                  <p>But he that heareth, <hi>and doth not,</hi> is like a man that without a foundation built an houſe upon the earth. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 47, 48, 49.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If we ſuffer,</hi> we ſhall alſo raign with him: <hi>if we deny him,</hi> he will alſo deny us. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
                  <p>If children, then heirs, heirs of God, and joynt-heirs of Chriſt: <hi>if ſo be that we ſuffer with him,</hi> that we may be alſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified together. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:169998:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Remiſsion of ſins by Christ.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHo ſhall have remiſſion of ſins by Chriſt? What ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Peter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To him give all the prophets wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that through his name <hi>whoſoever believeth in him,</hi> ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins. <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 43.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not Chriſt himſelf forgive ſins? What ſaith the Apoſtle Paul?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As Chriſt <hi>forgave you,</hi> ſo alſo do ye. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> When Chriſt forgave ſins on the earth, did he forgive them as being God, or as being a man impowered by God? Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe when he now forgiveth ſins in heaven, doth he forgive them as God, or as one exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God to that end? Cite the Scriptures pertinent hereunto.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus ſeeing their faith, ſaith to the ſick of the palſey, Son, be of good chear; thy ſins be forgiven thee.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169998:45"/>
                  <p>And behold, certain of the Scribes ſaid within themſelves, This man bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemeth.</p>
                  <p>And Jeſus knowing their thoughts, ſaid, Wherefore think ye evil in your hearts?</p>
                  <p>For whether is eaſier to ſay, Thy ſins be forgiven thee, or to ſay, Ariſe and walk?</p>
                  <p>But that ye may know that <hi>the Son of man hath power on earth to forgive ſins,</hi> (then ſpeaketh he to the ſick of the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey) Ariſe, take up thy bed, and go unto thine houſe.</p>
                  <p>And he aroſe, and departed to his houſe.</p>
                  <p>And when the multitude ſaw it, they marvelled, and glorified God, <hi>which had given ſuch power to men. Matth.</hi> 9. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>Him hath God exalted to be a Prince and Saviour, <hi>for to give repentance and remiſſion of ſins to Iſrael. Act.</hi> 5. 31.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:169998:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Chriſts Kingly Office.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WAs not Chriſt Jeſus to be a King? what ſaith the angel Gabriel to the virgin Mary concerning this?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Behold, thou ſhalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a ſon, and ſhalt call his name Jeſus.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall be great, and ſhall be called the Son of the Higheſt, and the Lord God ſhall give unto him <hi>the throne of David his father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he ſhall raign over the houſe of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob for ever, and of his kingdom there ſhall be no end. Luke</hi> 1. 31, 32, 33.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is Chriſt Jeſus already inveſted in his kingdom, and did he after his aſcenſion into heaven, and ſitting at the right hand of God, exerciſe dominion and ſoveraignty over men and angels? Rehearſe ſome clear paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the Scripture to this purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That ye may know,</p>
                  <p>What is the exceeding greatneſs of his power to us-ward who believe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169998:46"/> to the working of his mighty power:</p>
                  <p>Which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead, and ſet him at his own right hand in the heavenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Far above all principality, and power, and might, and dominion, and every name that is named not onely in this world, but alſo in that which is to come:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And hath put all things under his feet, and gave him to be head over all things to the Church, which is his body, the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all. Epheſ.</hi> 1. 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
                  <p>By the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt:</p>
                  <p>Who is gone into Heaven, and is on the right hand of God, <hi>angels, and authorities, and powers, being made ſubject to him.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21, 22.</p>
                  <p>And from Jeſus Chriſt, who is the faithful witneſs, and the firſt-begotten of the dead, <hi>and Prince of the kings of the earth:</hi> Unto him that hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood,</p>
                  <p>And hath made us kings and prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God even his Father; to him be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169998:46"/> and dominion for ever and ever. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 5, 6.</p>
                  <p>Him hath God exalted with his right hand <hi>to be a Prince and Saviour, for to give repentance to Iſrael, and forgiveneſs of ſins. Acts</hi> 5. 30, 31.</p>
                  <p>To him that overcometh will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, even as I overcame, and <hi>am ſet with my Father in his throne. Rev.</hi> 3. 21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I Jeſus have ſent mine angel,</hi> to teſtifie unto you theſe things in the Churches. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 16.</p>
                  <p>Brother Saul, <hi>the Lord (even Jeſus that appeared unto thee in the way as thou cameſt) hath ſent me,</hi> that thou mightſt receive thy ſight, and be filled with the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 17.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſhall make war with the Lamb, and the Lamb ſhall overcome them: for <hi>he is Lord of lords, and King of kings. Rev.</hi> 17. 14.</p>
                  <p>He was clothed with a veſture dipt in blood, and his name is called, The word of God.</p>
                  <p>And he hath on his veſture, and on his thigh a name written, <hi>King of kings, and Lord of lords. Rev.</hi> 19. 13, 16.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169998:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All power is given unto me in heaven and earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Go ge therefore and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you: and lo, <hi>I am with you always even unto the end of the world. Matth.</hi> 28. 18, 19, 20.</p>
                  <p>So then after the Lord had ſpoken to them, he was received up into heaven, and ſate on the right hand of God.</p>
                  <p>And they went forth and preached everywhere, <hi>the Lord working with them, and confirming the word with ſignes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Mark</hi> 16. 19, 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> For what cauſe, and to what ends was Chriſt Jeſus exalted to his kingdom?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the croſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherefore</hi> God alſo hath highly exalted him, and given him a name which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove every name, <hi>that at the name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow,</hi> of things in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and things in earth, and things under the earth:</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169998:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And that every tongue ſhould confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the glory of God the Father. Phil.</hi> 2. 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>Him hath God exalted with his right hand to be a Prince and Saviour, <hi>to give repentance to Iſrael, and forgiveneſs of ſins. Acts</hi> 5. 31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How ought men to honour the Son of God Chriſt Jeſus?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Even as they honour the Father. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What danger is there in not honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Son?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He that honoureth not the Son, honoureth not the Father that ſent him. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Ought men to honour the Son as they honour the Father, becauſe he hath <hi>the ſame eſſence</hi> with the Father, or becauſe he hath <hi>the ſame judiciary power?</hi> What is the deciſion of the Son himſelf concerning this point?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Father judgeth no man, but <hi>hath committed all judgement unto the Son:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That all men ſhould honour the Son, even as they honour the Father. Joh.</hi> 5. 22, 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did the Father give judiciary power to the Son, becauſe he had in him <hi>the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:169998:48"/> 
                     <hi>nature perſonally united to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> or becauſe he was <hi>the Son of man?</hi> What is the deciſion of the Son himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this point alſo?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He hath given him authority to execute judgement, becauſe he is <hi>the Son of man. Joh.</hi> 5. 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is it the will of God that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould be worſhipped of angels and men?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When he bringeth the firſt-begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into the world, he ſaith, <hi>And let all the angels of God worſhip him. Heb.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
                  <p>God hath highly exalted him, and given him a name which is above every name:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That at the name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow, of things in heaven, and things in earth. Phil.</hi> 2. 9, 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did men worſhip Jeſus Chriſt before his death and reſurrection? what examples thereof have you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Then they that were in the ſhip, came and <hi>worſhipped him,</hi> ſaying, Of a truth thou art the Son of God. <hi>Matth.</hi> 14. 33.</p>
                  <p>Jeſus ſaid unto him, Doſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on the Son of God? He anſwered
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169998:48"/> and ſaid, Who is he, Lord, that I may believe on him?</p>
                  <p>And Jeſus ſaid unto him, Thou haſt both ſeen him, and it is he that talketh with thee.</p>
                  <p>And he ſaid, Lord, I believe: and he <hi>worſhipped him. Joh.</hi> 9. 35, 36. 37, 38.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did men worſhip Chriſt after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and aſcenſion? And what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample thereof have you?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It came to paſs while he bleſſed them, he was parted from them, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried up into heaven:</p>
                  <p>And they <hi>worſhipped him,</hi> and returned to Jeruſalem, with great joy. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 51, 52.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> When men aſcribe glory and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to Chriſt Jeſus in the Scripture, and withal intimate the ground thereof, is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they conceive him to be <hi>very God of very God, and to have been eternally begotten out of the Divine eſſence,</hi> or becauſe <hi>he gave himſelf to death?</hi> Let me hear how they explain themſelves.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Unto him that hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood,</p>
                  <p>And hath made us Kings and Prieſts
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169998:49"/> unto God even his Father; <hi>to him</hi> be glory and dominion for ever and ever. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 5, 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Are the Angels of the ſame opinion with the Saints, when they alſo aſcribe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and dominion to him? <hi>let me hear how they alſo explain themſelves.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I beheld, and heard the voice of many angels, ſaying with a loud voice, Worthy is the Lamb <hi>that was ſlain,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive power, and riches, and wiſdom, and ſtrength, and honour, and glory, and bleſſing. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 11, 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> May men call upon the name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? and have you examples of ſuch as have prayed to him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Then Ananias anſwered, Lord, I have heard by many, of this man, how much evil he hath done to thy Saints at Jeruſalem:</p>
                  <p>And here he hath authority from the chief prieſts, to binde all <hi>that call upon thy name. Acts</hi> 9. 13, 13.</p>
                  <p>With all <hi>that in every place call upon the name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, both theirs and ours.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2.</p>
                  <p>And they ſtoned Stephen, ſaying, Lord Jeſus, receive my ſpirit. <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 59.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:169998:49"/>
                  <p>Even ſo, come, Lord Jeſus. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 20.</p>
                  <p>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, which hath loved us, and hath given us everlaſting conſolation, and a good hope through grace,</p>
                  <p>Comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in every good word and work. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>Now God himſelf even our Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt direct our way unto you. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of Chriſts Prieſtly Office.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> IS not Chriſt Jeſus a Prieſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We have a great high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt, Jeſus the Son of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did not Chriſt take this honour to himſelf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt glorified not himſelf to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an high-prieſt: but he that ſaid unto him, Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What maner of high-prieſt is Chriſt?</head>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:169998:50"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Such an high-prieſt, who is ſet on the right hand of the throne of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in the heavens:</p>
                  <p>A miniſter of the ſanctuary, and of the tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, and not man. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 1, 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Was not Chriſt a prieſt whilſt he was on earth, namely when he died on he croſs?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If he were on earth, he ſhould not be a prieſt, ſeeing that there are prieſts who offer gifts according to the Law. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 4.</p>
                  <p>And it is yet far more evident: for that after the ſimilitude of Melchiſedeck there ariſeth another prieſt,</p>
                  <p>Who is made, not after the law of a carnal commandment, but <hi>after the power of an endleſs life. Heb.</hi> 7. 15, 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What benefit happeneth by Chriſts prieſthood?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He became the author of eternal ſalvation,</p>
                  <p>Called of God an high-prieſt after the order of Melchiſedeck. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 9, 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Unto whom is Chriſt, as a Prieſt, become the authour of eternal ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</head>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:169998:50"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Unto all them that obey him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How can Chriſt ſave them by his prieſthood?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He is able to ſave them to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt, that come unto God by him, <hi>ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them. Heb.</hi> 7. 25.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt was once offered to bear the ſins of many. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is not the ſacrifice of Chriſt to be reiterated, as that of the Levitical Prieſts? if not, what is the reaſon thereof?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Every prieſt ſtandeth daily mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring and offering oftentimes the ſame ſacrifices, which can never take away ſins.</p>
                  <p>But this man, after he had offered one ſacrifice for ſins for ever, ſate down at the right hand of God: from henceforth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting till his enemies be made his footſtool.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified. Heb.</hi> 10. 11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How did Chriſt enter into the holy place to offer himſelf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By his own blood. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:169998:51"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Why would God have Chriſt come to his prieſtly office by ſufferings?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many ſons unto glory, to make the Captain of their ſalvation perfect through ſufferings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That he might be a merciful and faithful high-prieſt</hi> in things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the ſins of the people.</p>
                  <p>For in that he himſelf hath ſuffered, being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 10, 17, 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the true and genuine uſe you would have us make of this doctrine?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Seeing that we have a great high-prieſt, that is paſſed into the heavens, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Son of God, <hi>let us hold faſt our profeſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For we have not an high-prieſt that cannot be touched with a feeling of our infirmities: but was in all points tempted like as we are, yet without ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let us therefore come boldly unto the throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy, and finde grace</hi> to help in time of need. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 14, 15, 16.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:169998:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of Chriſts Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WAs it the will and purpoſe of God that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer the death of the croſs? What ſaith the apoſtle Peter to the Jews concerning this?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus of Nazareth a man approved of God among you,</p>
                  <p>Him being delivered <hi>by the determinate counſel and foreknowledge of God,</hi> ye have taken, and by wicked hands have cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſlain. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 22, 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What ſay the diſciples in general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame?</head>
                  <p>They lift up their voice to God with one accord, and ſaid,</p>
                  <p>Of a truth againſt thy holy childe Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, whom thou haſt anointed, both He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, and Pontius Pilate, with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and the people of Iſrael, were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together,</p>
                  <p>For to do <hi>whatſoever thy hand and thy counſel determined before to be done. Acts</hi> 4. 24, 27, 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:169998:52"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Did Chriſt die to reconcile and bring God to us, or on the contrary, to reconcile and bring us to God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When we were enemies <hi>we were reconciled to God</hi> by the death of his Son. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 10.</p>
                  <p>He is our peace, who hath made both one.</p>
                  <p>That he might <hi>reconcile both unto God</hi> in one body by the croſs, having ſlain the enmity thereby. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 14, 16.</p>
                  <p>God was in Chriſt <hi>reconciling the world to himſelf.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, that he might <hi>bring us to God.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> For whom did Chriſt die?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We thus judge, that if one died for all, then were all dead.</p>
                  <p>And that he <hi>died for all,</hi> that they which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but unto him which died for them, and roſe again. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>There is one Mediator between God and men, the man Chriſt Jeſus,</p>
                  <p>Who <hi>gave himſelf a ranſome for all,</hi> to be teſtified in due time. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5, 6.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:169998:52"/>
                  <p>We ſee Jeſus, who was made a little lower then the angels, for the ſuffering of death, crowned with glory and honour, that he by the grace of God <hi>ſhould taſte death for every man. Heb.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
                  <p>I am the living bread, which came down from heaven: if any man eat of this bread, he ſhall live for ever: and the bread that I will give, is my fleſh, which I will give <hi>for the life of the world. Joh.</hi> 6. 51.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What was the procuring cauſe of Chriſts death?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He was delivered <hi>for our offences. Rom.</hi> 4. 25.</p>
                  <p>He was wounded <hi>for our tranſgreſſions,</hi> he was bruiſed <hi>for our iniquities. Iſai.</hi> 53. 5.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt died <hi>for our ſins,</hi> according to the Scriptures. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What are the ends of Chriſts ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and death, intimated by the Scripture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. He learned obedience</hi> by the things which he ſuffered. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 8.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſuffered for you, <hi>leaving us an example,</hi> that ye ſhould follow his ſteps. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 21.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſins, the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169998:53"/> juſt for the unjuſt, that he <hi>might bring us to God.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18.</p>
                  <p>This is my blood of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>(or,</hi> New Covenant) that is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 28.</p>
                  <p>That through death <hi>he might deſtroy him that had the power of death,</hi> that is, the devil;</p>
                  <p>And deliver them, who through fear of death were all their life-time ſubject unto bondage. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>That he might ſanctifie the people with his own blood. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 12.</p>
                  <p>That whether we wake or ſleep, <hi>we ſhould live together with him.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
                  <p>That they which live, <hi>ſhould not hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth live to themſelves,</hi> but to him which died for them, and roſe again. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 15.</p>
                  <p>Who gave himſelf for our ſins, that <hi>he might deliver us from this preſent evil world. Gal.</hi> 1. 4.</p>
                  <p>Ye who were ſometimes far off, <hi>are made nigh</hi> by the blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>For he is our peace, who hath made both one, and hath broken down
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169998:53"/> the middle wall of partition between us:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having aboliſhed in his fleſh the law of commandments in ordinances, for to make in himſelf of twain, one new man, ſo making peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the croſs, having ſlain the enmity thereby. Eph.</hi> 2. 13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>It pleaſed the Father that in him all fulneſs ſhould dwell,</p>
                  <p>And <hi>having made peace through the blood of his croſs, by him to reconcile all things to himſelf</hi> (or rather, <hi>for him) by him,</hi> I ſay, whether they be things in earth, or things in heaven.</p>
                  <p>And you that were ſometimes aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and enemies in your minde by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked works, yet <hi>now hath he reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the body of his fleſh through death. Col.</hi> 1. 20, 21, 22.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:169998:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of the Univerſality of Gods love.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> THoſe Scriptures which you have already alleadged, when I enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for whom Chriſt died, intimate the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of Gods love to men: yet ſoraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as this is a point of the greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, without the knowledge and belief whereof, we cannot have any true and ſolid ground of coming unto God, (becauſe if he from all eternity intended good onely to a few, and thoſe few are not ſet down in the Scriptures, (which were written that we through comfort of them might have hope, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 4.) no man can certainly, yea pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably infer that he is in the number of thoſe few, the contrary being, ten thouſand to one, more likely) what other clear taſſages of Scripture have you, which ſhew, that God, in ſending Chriſt, and propoſing the Goſpel, ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not at the ſalvation of a certain elect number, but of men in general?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God ſo loved <hi>the world,</hi> that he gave his onely-begotten Son, that <hi>whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:169998:54"/> believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</p>
                  <p>For God ſent not his Son into the world, to condemn the world, but that <hi>the world</hi> through him might be ſaved. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>The bread of God is he which cometh down from heaven, and giveth life <hi>to the world. Joh.</hi> 6. 33.</p>
                  <p>Now we believe, not becauſe of thy ſaying, for we have heard him our ſelves, and know that this is indeed the Chriſt the Saviour of <hi>the world. Joh.</hi> 4. 42.</p>
                  <p>We have ſeen and do teſtifie, that the Father ſent the Son to be the Saviour <hi>of the world.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 14.</p>
                  <p>I am come a light into the world, that <hi>whoſoever</hi> believeth on me, ſhould not abide in darkneſs.</p>
                  <p>And if any man hear my words, and believe not, I judge him not: for I came not to judge the world, but to ſave <hi>the world. Joh.</hi> 12. 46, 47.</p>
                  <p>Go ye into <hi>all the world,</hi> and preach the Goſpel <hi>to every creature:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved: but he that believeth not, ſhall be condemned. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 15, 16.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:169998:55"/>
                  <p>If ye continue in the faith grounded and ſetled, and be not moved away from the hope of the Goſpel which ye have heard, and which was preached <hi>to every creature which is under heaven,</hi> whereof I Paul am made a miniſter. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 22.</p>
                  <p>We preach, warning <hi>every man,</hi> and teaching <hi>every man</hi> in all wiſdom, that we may preſent <hi>every man</hi> perfect in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 28.</p>
                  <p>I exhort that ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks, be made for <hi>all men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour,</p>
                  <p>WHO WILL HAVE ALL MEN TO BE SAVED, AND TO COME UNTO THE KNOWLEDGE OF THE TRUTH. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1, 3, 4.</p>
                  <p>The Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe, (as ſome men count ſlackneſs) but is long-ſuffering to us-ward, NOT WILLING THAT ANY SHOULD PERISH, BUT THAT ALL SHOULD COME TO REPENTANCE, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
                  <p>God was in Chriſt reconciling <hi>the world</hi> to himſelf, not imputing their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169998:55"/> treſpaſſes to them. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19.</p>
                  <p>We have an Advocate with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous:</p>
                  <p>And he is the propitiation for our ſins: and not for ours onely, but alſo for the ſins <hi>of the whole world.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 1, 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Theſe texts which you have now ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are all taken out of the New Teſtament; is there not a like manifeſtation of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of Gods love in the Old? How ſpeaketh the prophet Ezekiel?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Say unto them, As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked turn from his way, and live: turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways; for why will ye die, <hi>O houſe of Iſrael? Ezek.</hi> 33. 11.</p>
                  <p>Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, whereby ye have tranſgreſſed, and make you a new heart, and a new ſpirit; for why will ye die, <hi>O houſe of Iſrael?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For I have no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth, ſaith the Lord God: wherefore turn your ſelves, and live ye. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 31, 32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:169998:56"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith Jeremiah?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 33.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith David?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord is gracious, and full of compaſſion: ſlow to anger, and of great mercy.</p>
                  <p>The Lord is good <hi>to all:</hi> and his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies are over <hi>all his works. Pſal.</hi> 145. 8, 9.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of Chriſts Reſurrection.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Ought Chriſt, as to ſuffer, ſo alſo to riſe from the dead the third day?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thus it is written, and thus it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and <hi>to riſe from the dead the third day.</hi> Luke 24. 46.</p>
                  <p>He roſe again the third day, according to the Scriptures. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Was there ſo great power and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in Chriſts reſurrection? How ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Paul?</head>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:169998:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I count all things but loſs, for the excellencie of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord.</p>
                  <p>That I may know him, and <hi>the power of his reſurrection. Phil.</hi> 3. 8, 10.</p>
                  <p>If Chriſt be not riſen, your faith is vain, ye are yet in your ſins.</p>
                  <p>Then they alſo that are fallen aſleep in Chriſt, are periſhed. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>It is Chriſt that died, <hi>yea rather that is riſen again. Rom.</hi> 8. 34.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How ſpeaketh Peter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his abundant mercy, <hi>hath begotten us again unto a lively hope, by the reſurrection of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt from the dead.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did Chriſt riſe by his own power, yea did he raiſe himſelf at all? or was he raiſed by the power of another, and did ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raiſe him? What is the perpetual tenour of the Scripture to this purpoſe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Though he was crucified through weakneſs, yet he liveth <hi>by the power of God.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 4.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt was raiſed up from the dead <hi>by the glory of the Father. Rom.</hi> 6. 4.</p>
                  <p>By Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169998:57"/> 
                     <hi>who raiſed him from the dead. Gal.</hi> 1. 1.</p>
                  <p>If the Spirit <hi>of him that raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt from the dead,</hi> dwell in you; <hi>he that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead,</hi> ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo quicken your mortal bodies, by his Spirit that dwelleth in you. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He which raiſed up the Lord Jeſus,</hi> ſhall raiſe up us alſo by Jeſus. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 14.</p>
                  <p>Ye turned to God from idols, to ſerve the living and true God,</p>
                  <p>And to wait for his Son from heaven, <hi>whom he raiſed from the dead,</hi> even Jeſus which delivereth us from the wrath to come. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>Be it known unto you all, and to all the people of Iſrael, that by the Name of Jeſus Chriſt of Nazareth, whom ye crucified, <hi>whom God raiſed from the dead,</hi> even by him doth this man ſtand here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you whole. <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 10.</p>
                  <p>The God of peace <hi>that brought again from the dead</hi> our Lord Jeſus. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 20.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>God</hi> raiſed him from the dead.</p>
                  <p>God hath fulfilled the ſame unto us, in that <hi>he</hi> hath raiſed up Jeſus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:169998:57"/>
                  <p>And as concerning that <hi>he</hi> raiſed him up from the dead.</p>
                  <p>He whom <hi>God</hi> raiſed again, ſaw no corruption. <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 30, 33, 34, 37.</p>
                  <p>Him <hi>God</hi> raiſed up the third day. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 40.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God</hi> hath both raiſed up the Lord, and will alſo raiſe us up by his own power. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 14.</p>
                  <p>Who by him believe in <hi>God that raiſed him up from the dead,</hi> and gave him glory. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Were the Apoſtles and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit himſelf ſent to bear witneſs that Chriſt raiſed himſelf, or that God raiſed him? How ſpeaketh the Scripture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Jeſus hath God raiſed up, <hi>whereof we are all witneſſes. Acts</hi> 2. 32.</p>
                  <p>The God of Abraham, and of Iſaac, and of Jacob, the God of our fathers, hath glorified his Son Jeſus, whom ye delivered up; and denied him in the preſence of Pilate;</p>
                  <p>And killed the Prince of life, whom God hath raiſed from the dead, <hi>whereof we are witneſſes. Acts</hi> 3. 13, 15.</p>
                  <p>The God of our fathers raiſed up Jeſus.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:169998:58"/>
                  <p>Him hath God exalted with his right hand to be a Prince and Saviour,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And we are his witneſſes, of theſe things, and ſo is alſo the Holy Spirit,</hi> whom God hath given to all them that obey him. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 30, 31, 32.</p>
                  <p>We have teſtified of God, <hi>that he raiſed up Chriſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Of what conſequence is it to believe that Chriſt was thus raiſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and <hi>believe in thine heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved. Rom.</hi> 10. 9.</p>
                  <p>Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>Now it was not written for his ſake alone, that it was impured to him.</p>
                  <p>But for us, <hi>to whom it ſhall be imputed, if we believe on him that raiſed up Jeſus our Lord from the dead. Rom.</hi> 4. 3, 23, 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the prayer of the Apoſtle Paul to this purpoſe? How ſpeaketh be to the Epheſians?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That the God of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of glory, may give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the Spirit of wiſdom and revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the knowledge of him.</p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169998:58"/>
                  <p>The eyes of your underſtanding being enlightened, that ye may know,</p>
                  <p>What is the exceeding greatneſs of his power to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s-ward, who believe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the working of his mighty power,</p>
                  <p>Which he wrought in Chriſt, <hi>when he raiſed him from the dead. Eph.</hi> 1. 17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of Juſtification and Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> HOw many ſorts of juſtification or righteouſneſs are there?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The righteouſneſs, which is of the Law. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 5.</p>
                  <p>The righteouſneſs, which is of God by Faith. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How is the righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, deſcribed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Moſes deſcribeth the righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, <hi>that the man which doth thoſe things, ſhall live by them. Rom.</hi> 10. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How ſpeaketh the righteouſneſs
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169998:59"/> which is of Faith?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The righteouſneſs, which is of faith, ſpeaketh on this wiſe, Say not in thine heart, Who ſhall aſcend into heaven? that is to bring Chriſt down from above.</p>
                  <p>Or, who ſhall deſcend into the deep? that is to bring up Chriſt again from the dead. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 6, 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> But what ſaith it? Rom. 10. 8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in thine heart, that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> In the juſtification of a believer, is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to him? or is his own faith counted for righteouſneſs?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To him that worketh not, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on him that juſtifieth the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>his faith is counted for righteouſneſs. Rom.</hi> 4. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Was Abraham the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, juſtified in this maner?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He believed in the Lord, and he counted it to him for righteouſneſs. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Was not this written for his ſake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that it was imputed to him for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</head>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:169998:59"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It was not written for his ſake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that it was imputed to him:</p>
                  <p>But for us alſo. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 23, 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> On what terms? if we apprehend and apply Chriſts righteouſneſs to our ſelves?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If we believe on him that raiſed up Jeſus our Lord from the dead. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſs. Is it not ſufficient for us if we believe as he did? what ſaith Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Ye believe in God, believe alſo in me. <hi>John</hi> 14. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith Peter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt was manifeſted in theſe laſt times for you;</p>
                  <p>Who <hi>by</hi> (or, <hi>through) him believe on God.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 20, 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Doth not God juſtifie men, becauſe of the full price that Chriſt paid to him in their ſtead, ſo that he abated nothing of his right, in that one drop of Chriſts blood was ſufficient to ſatisfie for a thouſand Worlds? If not, how are they ſaved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Being juſtified FREELY by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:169998:60"/>
                  <p>In whom we have redemption through his blood, <hi>the forgiveneſs of ſins,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the riches of his grace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did not Chriſt merit eternal life, and purchaſe the kingdom of heaven for us?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>gift of God</hi> is eternal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23.</p>
                  <p>It is your Fathers <hi>good-pleaſure to give you</hi> the Kingdom. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 32.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of keeping the Commandments, and having an eye to the reward; of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in vertue and godlineſs to be attained; and of departing from righteouſneſs and faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> ARe the commandments poſſible to be kept?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> His commandments are not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
                  <p>My yoke is eaſie, and my burthen light. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 30.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> But though it be poſſible to keep the commandments, yet is it not enough if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169998:60"/> and endeavour to keep them, although we actually keep them not? And doth not God here accept the will for the deed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Circumciſion is nothing, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion is nothing, but <hi>the keeping of the commandments of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 19.</p>
                  <p>Not every one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven, but <hi>he that doth</hi> the will of my Father which is in heaven.</p>
                  <p>Therefore whoſoever heareth theſe ſayings of mine and <hi>doth them,</hi> I will liken him unto a wiſe man which built his houſe upon a rock.</p>
                  <p>And every one that heareth theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of mine and <hi>doth them not,</hi> ſhall be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened unto a fooliſh man which built his houſe upon the ſand. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 21, 24, 26.</p>
                  <p>Whoſo looketh into the perfect law of liberty, and continueth therein, he being not a forgetful hearer, but <hi>a doer of the work,</hi> ſhall be bleſſed <hi>in his doing. Jam.</hi> 1. 25.</p>
                  <p>Glory, honor, and peace to every man that <hi>worketh good,</hi> to the Jew firſt, and alſo to the Gentile. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
                  <p>If ye know theſe things, happy are ye <hi>if ye do them. Joh.</hi> 13. 17.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:169998:61"/>
                  <p>Bleſſed are they that hear the word of God, <hi>and keep it. Luke</hi> 11. 27.</p>
                  <p>We muſt all appear before the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat of Chriſt, that every man may receive the things <hi>done in his body,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what he hath <hi>done,</hi> whether it be good or evil. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10.</p>
                  <p>The Son of man ſhall come in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Father, with his angels, and then he ſhall reward every man <hi>according to his works. Mat.</hi> 16. 27.</p>
                  <p>Behold, I come quickly, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is with me, to give to every man according as <hi>his work</hi> ſhall be. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 12.</p>
                  <p>If thou wilt enter into life, <hi>keep the commandments. Mat.</hi> 19. 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Which? Mat. 19. 18.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt do no murther; Thou ſhalt not commit adultery; Thou ſhalt not ſteal; Thou ſhalt not bear falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Honor thy father and thy mother; and, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 18, 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Though it be not onely poſſible, but alſo neceſſary to keep the commandments, yet is it lawful ſo to do, that we may have a right to eternal life, and the heavenly inheritance? may we ſeek for honor, end glory, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169998:61"/> by well doing? is it the tenor of the Goſpel that we ſhould live uprightly in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the hope hereafter? and finally, ought we to ſuffer <hi>for</hi> the kingdom of God, and not (as ſume are pleaſed to mince the matter) <hi>from</hi> the kingdom of God? Cite the teſtimonies of the Scripture to this purpoſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Bleſſed are they that do his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, <hi>that they may have right to the tree of life, and may enter in through the gates into the city. Rev.</hi> 22. 14.</p>
                  <p>—The revelation of the righteous judgement of God:</p>
                  <p>Who will render to every man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his deeds.</p>
                  <p>To them, <hi>who by patient continuance in well-doing ſeek for glory, and honor, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality,</hi> eternal life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>The grace of God, that bringeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, hath appeared to all men,</p>
                  <p>Teaching us, that denying ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Looking for that bleſſed hope,</hi> and the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12, 13.</p>
                  <p>That ye may be counted worthy of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169998:62"/> the kingdom of God, <hi>for which</hi> ye alſo ſuffer. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have ye any Scripture that ſaith <hi>we muſt believe that God is a rewarder of them that ſeek him,</hi> and that if we come not to him with ſuch a faith, it is impoſſible to pleaſe him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe him: for he that cometh to God, muſt believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you any example of keeping the commandments under the law? what ſaith David of himſelf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord rewarded me according to my righteouſneſs, according to the cleanneſs of mine hands hath he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed me.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>I have kept the ways of the Lord,</hi> and have not wickedly departed from my God.</p>
                  <p>For all his judgments were before me, &amp; I did not put away his ſtatutes from me.</p>
                  <p>I was alſo upright before him: and I kept my ſelf from mine iniquity.</p>
                  <p>Therefore hath the Lord recompenced me according to my righteouſneſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cleanneſs of my hands in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169998:62"/> his eye-ſight. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 20, 21, 22, 23, 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you any example under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Whatſoever we ask, we receive of him, <hi>becauſe we keep his commandments,</hi> and do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight. 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you not examples of the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Saints, who obeyed God in hope of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, both before, under, and after the Law?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By faith. Abraham when he was called to go out into a place which he ſhould after receive for an inheritance, obeved, and he went out, not knowing whither he went.</p>
                  <p>By faith he ſojourned in the land of promiſe, as in a ſtrange country, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in tabernacles with Iſaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the ſame promiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For he looked for a city which hath foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, whoſe builder and maker is God. Heb.</hi> 11. 8, 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>By faith Moſes when he was come to yeers refuſed to be called the ſon of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs daughter;</p>
                  <p>Chuſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon:</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:169998:63"/>
                  <p>Eſteeming the reproach of Chriſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter riches then the treaſures in Egypt: <hi>for he had reſpect unto the recompence of the reward. Heb.</hi> 11. 24, 25, 26.</p>
                  <p>Let us run with patience the race that is ſet before us,</p>
                  <p>Looking unto Jeſus the author and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our faith, who <hi>for the joy that was ſet before him,</hi> endured the croſs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the throne of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 1, 2.</p>
                  <p>Paul, a ſervant of God, and an apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the faith of Gods elect, and the acknowledging of the truth, which is after godlineſs:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In hope of eternal life. Tit.</hi> 1. 1, 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Do not the Scriptures intimate that Chriſtians may attain to perfection of vertue and godlineſs? and that it is the intention of God, and Chriſt, and his miniſters, to bring them unto this pitch? Rehearſe the texts to this effect.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> According as he hath choſen us in him before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be <hi>holy and unblameable before him</hi> in love. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 4.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt loved the Church, and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169998:63"/> for it:</p>
                  <p>That he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the word.</p>
                  <p>That he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, <hi>not having ſpot or wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, or any ſuch thing:</hi> but that it ſhould be <hi>holy and without blemiſh. Eph.</hi> 5. 25, 26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Having therefore theſe promiſes, let us cleanſe our ſelves <hi>from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be ye perfect</hi> even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 48.</p>
                  <p>Finally, brethren, farewel: <hi>be ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 11.</p>
                  <p>We preach warning every man, and teaching every man in all wiſdom, that we may preſent every man <hi>perfect in Chriſt Jeſus. Col.</hi> 1. 28.</p>
                  <p>He gave ſome, apoſtles: ſome, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: ſome, evangeliſts! ſome, paſtors and teachers;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the perfecting of the ſaints,</hi> for the work of the miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt:</p>
                  <p>Till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169998:64"/> of God, <hi>unto a perfect man,</hi> unto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13.</p>
                  <p>Epaphras, who is one of you, a ſervant of Chriſt, ſaluteth you, always labouring fervently for you in prayers, that ye may <hi>ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God. Col.</hi> 4. 12.</p>
                  <p>The very God of peace ſanctifie you wholly: and I pray God <hi>your whole ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſoul, and body be preſerved blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs unto the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 23.</p>
                  <p>To the end he may ſtabliſh your hearts <hi>unblameable in holineſs before God even our Father,</hi> at the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with all his ſaints. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
                  <p>Now our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, which hath loved us, and given us everlaſting conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and good hope through grace,</p>
                  <p>Comfort your hearts, and <hi>ſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 16, 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you any example of perfection before the Law?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Noah was a juſt man, <hi>and perfect</hi> in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169998:64"/> his generations, and Noah walked with God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 9.</p>
                  <p>The Lord ſaid unto Satan, Haſt thou conſidered my ſervant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, <hi>a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God; and eſcheweth evil? Job.</hi> 1. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you any example of perfection under the Law?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> There was in the days of Herod the king of Judea, a certain prieſt named Zacharias, of the courſe of Abia; and his wife was of the daughters of Aaron, and her name was Elizabeth.</p>
                  <p>And they were both <hi>righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord, blameleſs. Luk.</hi> 1. 1, 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have you any examples under the Goſpel?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that ye ſhould follow his ſteps.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who did no ſin, neither was guile found in his mouth.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 21, 22.</p>
                  <p>I looked, and lo, a Lamb ſtood on the mount Sion, and with him an hundred fourty and four thouſand, having his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers name written on their foreheads.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:169998:65"/>
                  <p>Theſe are they which were not defiled with women, for they are virgins: theſe are they which follow the Lamb whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>in their mouth was found no guile: for they are without fault before the throne of God. Rev.</hi> 14. 1, 4, 5.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt a few names even in Sardis, <hi>which have not defiled their garments,</hi> and they ſhall walk with me in white, for they are worthy. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
                  <p>Ye are witneſſes, and God alſo, <hi>how holily, and juſtly, and unblameably we beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our ſelves among you that believe.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> If works be ſo neceſſary to ſalvation, as you have before ſhewn from the Scripture, how cometh it to paſs that Paul ſaith, We are juſtified by faith without works? Meant he to exclude all good works whatſoever, or onely thoſe of the Law? How doth he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain himſelf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We are juſtified by faith <hi>without the works of the Law. Rom.</hi> 3. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Can you make it appear from elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, that Paul intended to exclude from juſtification onely the perfect works of the Law, which leave no place for either grace
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169998:65"/> or faith, and not ſuch works as include both? and that by a juſtifying faith he meant a working faith, and ſuch a one as is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with righteouſneſs?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. By grace</hi> are ye ſaved, <hi>through faith,</hi> and that not of your ſelves: it is the gift of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not of works,</hi> leſt any man ſhould boaſt.</p>
                  <p>For we are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>unto good works,</hi> which God hath before ordained, that we ſhould walk in them. <hi>Eph.</hi> 8. 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>Now to him <hi>that worketh,</hi> is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward not reckoned <hi>of grase,</hi> but <hi>of debt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to him <hi>that worketh not, but belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly,</hi> his faith is counted for righteouſneſs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 4, 5.</p>
                  <p>There is a remnant according to the election of grace.</p>
                  <p>And if by <hi>grace,</hi> then it is no more of <hi>works:</hi> otherwiſe grace is no more grace. But if it be <hi>of works,</hi> then it is no more <hi>grace:</hi> otherwiſe work is no more work. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 5, 6.</p>
                  <p>If they which are of the law be heirs, faith is made void, and the promiſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169998:66"/> made of none effect.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe the law worketh wrath: for where no law is, there is no tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it is <hi>of faith,</hi> that it might be <hi>by grace:</hi> to the end the promiſe might be ſure to all the ſeed. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 14, 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>In Jeſus Chriſt neither circumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but faith <hi>working by love, God.</hi> 5. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The juſt</hi> ſhall live by faith.</p>
                  <p>For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven, againſt all ungodlineſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 17, 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What anſwer then would you give to a man, who wreſting the words of Paul in certain places of his Epiſtles to the Romans and the Galatians, ſhould bear you in hand, that all good works whatſoever are excluded from juſtification and ſalvation, and that it is enough onely to believe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead?</p>
                  <p>Was not Abraham our father juſtified by works, when he had offered Iſaac his ſon upon the altar?</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:169998:66"/>
                  <p>Seeſt, thou how faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect?</p>
                  <p>And the Scripture was fulfilled which ſaith, Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſs: and he was called the friend of God.</p>
                  <p>Ye ſee then how that by works a man is juſtified, and not by faith onely.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe alſo was not Rahab the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot juſtified by works, when ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the meſſengers, and had ſent them out another way?</p>
                  <p>For as the body without the ſpirit is dead, ſo faith without works is dead. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 20, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the advice of Paul to Titus concerning the buſineſs of faith, and works, and the Law?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This is a faithful ſaying, and theſe things I will that thou affirm conſtantly, <hi>that they which have believed in God, might be careful to maintain good works: theſe things are good and profitable unto men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But avoid fooliſh queſtions, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogies, and contentions, <hi>and ſtrivings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the law, for they are unprofitable and vain. Tit.</hi> 3. 8, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:169998:67"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> You ſhewed even now out of Paul, that the faith of him that will be ſaved, muſt be accompanied with juſtice or righteouſneſs; I would therefore know of you who is a juſt or righteous man? is it not ſuch a one <hi>as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth and applyeth Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to himſelf,</hi> or, at moſt, <hi>deſireth to do righteouſly?</hi> Is not he accepted of God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Let no man deceive you, <hi>he that doth righteouſneſs, is righteous,</hi> even as he is righteous.</p>
                  <p>He that committeth ſin, is of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, for the Divel ſinneth from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
                  <p>In this the children of God are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and the children of the Divel: <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 7, 8, 10.</p>
                  <p>If we know that he is righteous, know ye <hi>that every one that doth righteouſneſs is born of God.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 29</p>
                  <p>God is no reſpecter of perſons:</p>
                  <p>But in every nation, he that feareth him, <hi>and worketh righteouſneſs,</hi> is accepted of him. <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 34, 35.</p>
                  <p>If a man be juſt, and <hi>and do that which is lawful and right,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hath not eaten upon the mountains,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169998:67"/> neither hath lift up his eyes to the idols of the houſe of Iſrael, neither hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed his neighbours wife, neither hath come near to a menſtruous woman;</p>
                  <p>And hath not oppreſſed any, but hath reſtored to the debtor his pledge, hath ſpoiled none by violence, hath given his bread to the hungry, and hath covered the naked with a garment;</p>
                  <p>He hath not given forth upon uſury, neither hath taken any increaſe; hath withdrawn his hand from iniquity, hath executed true judgement between man and man;</p>
                  <p>Hath walked in my Statutes, and hath kept my judgements to deal truly, HE IS JUST, he ſhall not dye. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> May not righteous men depart from their righteouſneſs, and believers from their faith, and ſo periſh? And is it not falſe, that <hi>once in Chriſt, and ever in Chriſt?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the righteous turneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his righteouſneſs, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth iniquity, and doth according to all the abominations that the wicked man doth, ſhall he live? all his righteouſneſs, that he hath done, ſhall not be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169998:68"/> in his treſpaſs that he hath treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, and in his ſin that he hath ſinned, in them ſhall he dye. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 24.</p>
                  <p>When I ſhall ſay unto the righteous, that he ſhall ſurely live: if he truſt to his own righteouſneſs, and commit iniquity, all his righteouſneſs ſhall not be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, but for his iniquity that he hath committed he ſhall dye for it. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 13.</p>
                  <p>Now the Spirit ſpeaketh expreſsly, that in the latter times <hi>ſome ſhall depart from the faith,</hi> giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and doctrines of Divels. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1.</p>
                  <p>This charge I commit unto thee, ſon Timothy, that thou war the good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare:</p>
                  <p>Holding faith, and a good conſcience, <hi>which ſome having put away, concerning faith have made ſhipwrack.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of whom is Hymeneus and Alexander, whom I have delivered unto Satan, that they may learn not to blaſpheme. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 18, 19, 20.</p>
                  <p>The younger widows refuſe, for when they have begun to wax wanton againſt Chriſt, they will marry:</p>
                  <p>Having condemnation, becauſe <hi>they</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:169998:68"/> 
                     <hi>have caſt off their firſt faith.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>The love of money is the root of all evil, which while ſome coveted after, <hi>they have erred from the faith,</hi> and pierced themſelves through with many ſorrows. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 10.</p>
                  <p>Their word will eat as doth a canker, of whom is Hymeneus and Philetus:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who concerning the faith have erred,</hi> ſaying that the reſurrection is paſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>and overthrow the faith of ſome.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>Take heed, brethren, leſt there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief, <hi>in departing from the living God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But exhort one another daily, <hi>leſt any of you be hardened through the deceitfulneſs of ſin. Heb.</hi> 3. 12, 13.</p>
                  <p>Let us labour therefore to enter into that reſt, <hi>leſt any man fall after the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of unbelief. Heb.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
                  <p>It is impoſſible for thoſe who were once enlightned, and have taſted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the holy Ghoſt,</p>
                  <p>And have taſted the good word of God, and the powers of the world to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169998:69"/> come:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If they fall away, to renew them again to repentance. Heb.</hi> 6. 4, 5, 6.</p>
                  <p>Let us conſider one another, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke unto love and good works.</p>
                  <p>Not <hi>forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the maner of ſome is,</hi> but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting one another.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>if we ſin wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the truth,</hi> there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſins.</p>
                  <p>He that deſpiſed Moſes law, died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy, under two or three witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>Of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and <hi>hath counted the blood of the covenant, wherewith he was ſanctified, an unholy thing, and hath done deſpite to the Spirit of grace?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caſt not away therefore your confidence,</hi> which hath great recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                  <p>Now the juſt ſhall live by faith: <hi>but if any man draw back,</hi> my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But we are not of them that draw back unto perdition:</hi> but of them that believe to the ſaving of the ſoul. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 24,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169998:69"/> 25, 26, 28, 29, 35, 38, 39.</p>
                  <p>Looking diligently <hi>leſt any man fail of the grace of God. Heb.</hi> 12. 15.</p>
                  <p>Curſed children,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray,</hi> following the way of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam the ſon of Boſor, who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>When they ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity, they allure through the luſts of the fleſh, through much wantonneſs, thoſe <hi>that were clean eſcaped from them who live in error.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For if, after they have eſcaped the pollutions of the world through the knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, they <hi>are again entangled therein, and overcome,</hi> the latter end is worſe with them then the beginning.</p>
                  <p>For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs, then after they have known it, to <hi>turn from the holy commandment delivered to them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it is happened unto them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true proverb, The dog is turned to his vomit again; and the ſow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169998:70"/> mire. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 14, 15, 18, 20, 21, 22.</p>
                  <p>Ye therefore, beloved, ſeeing ye know theſe things before, beware <hi>leſt ye alſo being led away with the er or of the wicked, fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſs.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 17.</p>
                  <p>For this cauſe, when I could no longer forbear, I ſent to know your faith, <hi>leſt by ſome means the tempter had tempted you, and our labour be in vain.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe of unbelief they were broken off, and thou ſtandeſt by faith. Be not highminded, but fear.</p>
                  <p>For if God ſpared not the natural branches, take heed, <hi>leſt he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Behold therefore the goodneſs, and ſeverity of God: on them which fell, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity; but towards thee, goodneſs, <hi>if thou continue in goodneſs: otherwiſe thou alſo ſhalt be cut off. Rom.</hi> 11. 20, 21, 22.</p>
                  <p>But if thy brother be grieved with thy meat, now walkeſt thou not chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably. <hi>Deſtroy not him with thy meat, for whom Chriſt died. Rom.</hi> 14. 25.</p>
                  <p>Through thy knowledge <hi>ſhall the weak brother periſh, for whom Chriſt died?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 11.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:169998:70"/>
                  <p>I keep under my body, and bring it into ſubjection, <hi>leſt when I have preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt-away.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 27.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If a man abide not in me,</hi> he is caſt forth as a branch, and is withered. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Every branch in me that beareth not fruit,</hi> he taketh away. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 2.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of the duty of Subjects and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Wives and Husbands, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Parents, Servants and Maſters.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHat is the duty of all them that are under authority?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Let every foul <hi>be ſubject</hi> to the higher powers. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why muſt every ſoul be ſubject to them?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For there is no power but of God: the powers that be, are ordained of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:169998:71"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth he that reſiſteth the power; and what ſhall they receive to themſelves?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Whoſoever reſiſteth the power, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the ordinance of God: and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Why ſhall they that reſiſt, receive damnation?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For rulers are not a terrour to good works, but to evil. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How ſhall a man behave himſelf that he need not fear the power; and whence cometh it ſo to paſs?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power? do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>For he is the miniſter of God to thee for good: but if thou do that which is evil, be afraid: for he beareth not the ſword in vain: for he is the miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evil. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 3, 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is not the fear of wrath or puniſhment the onely motive to ſubjection?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Ye muſt needs be ſubject, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Muſt we not alſo pay to the higher powers tribute and cuſtom?</head>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:169998:71"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Render to all their dues, tribute to whom tribute is due, cuſtom to whom cuſtom. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why ſhould we pay tribute to them?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For this cauſe pay you tribute al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: for they are Gods miniſters, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding continually upon this very thing. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Though what you have cited out of the apoſtle Paul doth intimate the duty of the Magiſtrate, yet have you not ſome paſſage of Scripture that doth expreſly ſet it down?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What benefit ſhall accrue to him that ruleth ſo?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He ſhall be as the light of the morning, when the ſun riſeth, even a morning without clouds; as the tender graſs ſpringing out of the earth by clear ſhining after rain. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the duty of wives and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, according to the doctrine of the two great apoſtles, Paul and Peter? Rehearſe their words.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Wives, ſubmit your ſelves unto your own husbands, as unto the Lord.</p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:169998:72"/>
                  <p>For the husband is the head of the wife, even as Chriſt is the head of the church: and he is the Saviour of the body.</p>
                  <p>Therefore as the church is ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, ſo let wives be to their own husbands in every thing.</p>
                  <p>Husbands, love your wives, even as Chriſt alſo loved the church, and gave himſelf for it:</p>
                  <p>That he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water, by the word.</p>
                  <p>That he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious church, not having ſpot or wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, or any ſuch thing: but that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh.</p>
                  <p>So ought men to love their wives, as their own bodies: he that loveth his wife, loveth himſelf.</p>
                  <p>For no man ever yet hated his own fleſh: but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it, even as the Lord doth the church.</p>
                  <p>For we are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones.</p>
                  <p>For this cauſe ſhall a man leave his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, and ſhall cleave unto his wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſh.</p>
                  <p>This is a great myſtery: but I ſpeak
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169998:72"/> concerning Chriſt and the church.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs let every one of you in particular, ſo love his wife even as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the wife ſee that ſhe reverence her husband. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 22, 23, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Wives, ſubmit your ſelves unto your own husbands, as it is fit in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter againſt them. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 18, 19.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe, ye wives be in ſubjection to your own husbands, that if any obey not the word, they alſo may without the word be won by the converſation of the wives:</p>
                  <p>While they behold your chaſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation coupled with fear.</p>
                  <p>Whoſe adorning let it not be that outward adorning, of plaiting the hair, and of wearing gold, or of putting on of apparel:</p>
                  <p>But let it be the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price.</p>
                  <p>For after this maner in the old time, the holy women alſo who truſted in God adorned themſelves, being in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169998:73"/> unto their own husbands.</p>
                  <p>Even as Sarah obeyed Abraham, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him Lord, whoſe daughters ye are as long as ye do well, and are not afraid with any amazement.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe ye husbands, dwell with them according to knowledge, giving honor to the wife as unto the weaker veſſel, and as being heirs together of the grace of life, that your prayers be not hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the duty of children and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, according to Paul?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Children, obey your parents in the Lord: for this is right.</p>
                  <p>Honor thy father and thy mother (which is the firſt commandment with promiſe)</p>
                  <p>That it may be well with thee, and thou maiſt live long on the earth.</p>
                  <p>And ye fathers, provoke not your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to wrath, but bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
                  <p>Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is well pleaſing to the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Fathers, provoke not your children, leſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169998:73"/> they be diſcouraged. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 20, 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the duty of ſervants and maſters, according to the doctrine of the two aforeſaid Apoſtles?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Servants, be obedient to them that are your maſters according to the fleſh, with fear and trembling, in ſingleneſs of your heart, as unto Chriſt:</p>
                  <p>Not with eye-ſervice, as men-pleaſers, but as the ſervants of Chriſt, doing the will of God from the heart;</p>
                  <p>With good will doing ſervice as to the Lord, and not to men:</p>
                  <p>Knowing that whatſoever good thing any man doth, the ſame ſhall he receive of the Lord, whether he be bond or free.</p>
                  <p>And ye maſters, do the ſame things unto them, forbearing threatning: know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that your maſter alſo is in heaven, neither is there reſpect of perſons with him. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>Let as many ſervants as are under the yoke, count their own maſters worthy of all honour; that the Name of God, and his doctrine be not blaſphemed.</p>
                  <p>And they that have believing maſters, let them not deſpiſe them, becauſe they
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169998:74"/> are brethren: but rather do them ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, becauſe they are faithful and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, partakers of the benefit. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 1, 2.</p>
                  <p>Exhort ſervants to be obedient unto their own maſters, and to pleaſe them well in all things, not anſwering again:</p>
                  <p>Not purloyning, but ſhewing all good fidelity, that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>Servants, obey in all things your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters according to the fleſh: not with eye-ſervice, as men-pleaſers, but in ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, fearing God:</p>
                  <p>And whatſoever ye do, do it heartily, as to the Lord, and not unto men:</p>
                  <p>Knowing, that of the Lord ye ſhall receive the reward of the inheritance: for ye ſerve the Lord Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But he that doth wrong, ſhall receive for the wrong which he hath done: and there is no reſpect of perſons.</p>
                  <p>Maſters, give to your ſervants that which is juſt and equal, knowing that ye alſo have a Maſter in heaven. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 1.</p>
                  <p>Servants, be ſubject to your maſters
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169998:74"/> with all fear, not onely to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward.</p>
                  <p>For this is thank-worthy, if a man for conſcience toward God endure grief, ſuffering wrongfully.</p>
                  <p>For what glory is it, if when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye ſhall take it patiently? but if when ye do well, and ſuffer for it, ye take it patiently; this is acceptable with God.</p>
                  <p>For even hereunto are ye called; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us an example, that ye ſhould follow his ſteps. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 18, 19, 20, 21.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Of the behaviour of men and women in general; and in ſpecial of aged men, aged women, yong women, and yong men.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHat would the apoſtle Paul have men in general do? How ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I will that men pray everywhere,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169998:75"/> lifting up holy hands, without wrath and doubting.</p>
                  <p>In like maner alſo, that women adorn themſelves in modeſt apparel, with ſhamefac'dneſs and ſobriety: not with broidered hair, or gold, or pearls, or coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aray;</p>
                  <p>But (which becometh women profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing godlineſs) with good works.</p>
                  <p>Let the women learn in ſilence with all ſubjection.</p>
                  <p>But I ſuffer not a woman to teach, nor to uſurp authority over the man, but to be in ſilence. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>But ſpeak thou the things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſound doctrine.</p>
                  <p>That the aged men be ſober, grave, temperate, ſound in faith, in charity, in patience.</p>
                  <p>The aged women likewiſe that they be in behaviour as becometh holineſs, not falſe accuſers, not given to much wine, teachers of good things.</p>
                  <p>That they may teach the yong women to be ſober, to love their husbands, to love their children,</p>
                  <p>To be diſcreet, chaſte, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169998:75"/> that the word of God be not blaſphemed.</p>
                  <p>Yong men likewiſe exhort to be ſober-minded. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 1, 2, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Of Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> IS not Prayer a Chriſtian duty?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Pray without ceaſing. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 17.</p>
                  <p>And he ſpake a parable unto them, to this end, that men ought always to pray, and not to faint. <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ought men to pray?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Lifting up holy hands, without wrath and doubting. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What if a man doubt or waver as he prayeth?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Let not that man think that he ſhall receive any thing of the Lord. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What if we pray in anger, and do not forgive, if we have ought againſt any?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If you do not forgive, neither will your Father which is in heaven forgive your treſpaſſes. <hi>Mark</hi> 11. 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:169998:76"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What then is the confidence that we have to God-ward in praying?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That if we ask any thing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will, he heareth us. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> If a man ſee his brother ſin a ſin which is not unto death, what is his duty in relation to prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He ſhall ask, and he ſhall give him life for them that ſin not unto death. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What if he ſin a ſin which is unto death?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I do not ſay that he ſhall pray for it. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How are the perſons that have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unpardonably, and ſo unto death, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the Scripture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He that ſhall blaſpheme againſt the holy Ghoſt, hath never forgiveneſs, but is in danger of eternal damnation.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe they ſaid, He hath an unclean ſpirit. <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 29, 30.</p>
                  <p>If we ſin wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſins,</p>
                  <p>But a certain fearful looking for of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169998:76"/> judgement, and fiery indignation, which ſhall devour the adverſaries.</p>
                  <p>He that deſpiſed Moſes law, died without mercy, under two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
                  <p>Of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant wherewith he was ſanctified, an unholy thing, <hi>and hath done deſpite unto the Spirit of grace? Heb.</hi> 10. 26, 27, 28, 29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How ſtands the Lord affected to them that call upon him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord is nigh to all that call upon him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 18.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Lord over all, is rich unto all that call upon him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is he nigh unto all them that call upon him in whatſoever maner?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To all that call upon him in truth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 18.</p>
                  <p>The Lord is far from the wicked: but he heareth the prayer of the righteous. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 29.</p>
                  <p>We know that God heareth not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: but if any man be a worſhipper of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169998:77"/> God, and doth his will, him he heareth. <hi>John</hi> 9. 31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Did not Chriſt himſelf preſcribe a form of prayer to his diſciples, ſo that there remaineth no doubt touching the lawfulneſs of uſing a form?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It came to paſs, that as he was praying in a certain place, when he ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, one of his diſciples ſaid unto him, Lord, teach us to pray, as John alſo taught his diſciples.</p>
                  <p>And he ſaid unto them, when ye pray, ſay, Our Father which art in heaven, Hallowed be thy name. Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done as in heaven, ſo on earth.</p>
                  <p>Give us day by day our daily bread.</p>
                  <p>And forgive us our ſins; for we alſo forgive every one that is indebted to us. And lead us not into temptation, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from evil. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How muſt we make our addreſſes to the Father that we may receive whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we pray for? what ſaith Chriſt to his diſciples?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Verily, verily I ſay unto you, What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye ſhall ask the Father in my name, he will give it you. <hi>John</hi> 16. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:169998:77"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Was it the cuſtome, during the time that Chriſt converſed on the earth, (much leſs before he came into the world) to pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God in the name of Chriſt, or through Chriſt? or did it begin to be uſed after the reſurrection and exaltation of Chriſt? what ſaith Chriſt himſelf concerning this?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Hitherto have ye asked nothing in my name: ask, and ye ſhall receive, that your joy may be full.</p>
                  <p>The time cometh when I ſhall no more ſpeak unto you in parables, but I ſhall ſhew you plainly of the Father.</p>
                  <p>At that day ye ſhall ask in my name. <hi>John</hi> 16. 24, 25, 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Have ye any example of praying to God through Chriſt after his reſurrection, and exaltation?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Now the God of peace that brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus, that great ſhepherd of the ſheep, through the blood of the everlaſting co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</p>
                  <p>Make you perfect in every good work to do his will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, <hi>through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 20, 21.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:169998:78"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Of the Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHat is Chriſt in relation to the Church, and the Church in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He is the head of the body, the Church. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How many ſuch bodyes hath Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> One body. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What kind of head is Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> From which all the body by joynts and bands having nouriſhment miniſtred, and knit together, increaſeth with the increaſe of God. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Who are the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be ſaints 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Upon what foundation is the Church built?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Upon the foundation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf being the chief corner-ſtone. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What other honourable titles doth
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169998:78"/> the Scripture give unto the Church, beſides that of the body of Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The bride the Lambs wife. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 7, 8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 9.</p>
                  <p>The temple of God. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
                  <p>The houſe of God, the pillar and ground of the truth. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What ſpecial promiſe hath Chriſt made to the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What doth Chriſt elſewhere ſay of himſelf, that may give aſſurance to the Church that this promiſe ſhall be made good?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Behold, I live for ever and ever, amen; <hi>and have the keys of hell and death. Rev.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>Of the Government and Diſcipline of the Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHen Chriſt was aſcended up on high after his death and reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and ſo ceaſed to be perſonally preſent
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169998:79"/> with his Church, whom did he ſet apart for the perfecting of the ſaints, for the work of the miniſtry, for the edifying of his body?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He gave ſome, Apoſtles: and ſome, Prophets: and ſome, Evangeliſts: and ſome, Paſtors and Teachers;</p>
                  <p>For the perfecting of the ſaints, for the work of the miniſtry, for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body of Chriſt:</p>
                  <p>Till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the advice of the two great Apoſtles Paul and Peter to the elders and governors of the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Take heed unto your ſelves, and to all the flock, over the which the holy Ghoſt hath made your overſeers, to feed the Church of God, which he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with his own blood. <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28.</p>
                  <p>The elders which are among you I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, who am alſo an elder, and a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſufferings of Chriſt, and alſo a partaker of the glory that ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed:</p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:169998:79"/>
                  <p>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly: not for filthy lucre, but of a ready minde.</p>
                  <p>Neither as being lords over Gods he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage: but being enſamples to the flock. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What reward doth the apoſtle Peter tell them they ſhall have at the appearance of Chriſt, if they do as he preſcribeth?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the duty of the yonger, or private ſort, in relation to the elders or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like officers of the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Likewiſe ye yongers, ſubmit your ſelves unto the elders. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
                  <p>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves: for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give account: that they may do it with joy, and not with grief: for that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable for you. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17.</p>
                  <p>We beſeech you, brethren, to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you;</p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:169998:80"/>
                  <p>And to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 12, 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What ſaith the Scripture concorning the maintenance of them that inſtruct and overſee the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Let him that is taught in the word, communicate unto him that teacheth, in all good things.</p>
                  <p>Be not deceived, God is not mocked: for whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap.</p>
                  <p>For he that ſoweth to his fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption: but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap life everlaſting. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6: 6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>If we have ſown unto you ſpiritual things, is it a great thing if we ſhall reap your carnal things?</p>
                  <p>Do ye not know that they which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter about holy things, live of the things of the temple? and they which wait at the altar, are partakers with the altar?</p>
                  <p>Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the goſpel, ſhould live of the goſpel. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 11, 13, 14.</p>
                  <p>Let the elders that rule well, be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169998:80"/> worthy of double honour, eſpecially they who labour in the word and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
                  <p>For the Scripture ſaith, Thou ſhalt not muzzle the ox that treadeth out the corn; and, The labourer is worthy of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17, 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith the apoſtle Paul to Titus concerning the perſons that are to be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Elders, Biſhops, or Overſeers of the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For this cauſe left I thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldſt ſet in order the things that are wanting, and ordain elders in every city, as I had appointed thee.</p>
                  <p>If any be blameleſs, the husband of one wife, having faithful children, not accuſed of riot, or unruly.</p>
                  <p>For a biſhop muſt be blameleſs, as the ſteward of God: not ſelf-willed, not ſoon angry, not given to wine, no ſtriker, not given to filthy lucre;</p>
                  <p>But a lover of hoſpitality, a lover of good men, ſober, juſt, holy, temperate,</p>
                  <p>Holding faſt the faithful word, as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound doctrine, both to exhort and to convince gainſayers. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:169998:81"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſaith he to Timothy concerning the ſame ſubject?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This is a true ſaying, If any man deſire the office of a biſhop, he deſireth a good work.</p>
                  <p>A biſhop then muſt be blameleſs, the husband of one wife, vigilant, ſober, of good behaviour, given to hoſpitality, apt to teach;</p>
                  <p>Not given to wine, no ſtriker, not given to filthy lucre, but patient, not a brawler, not covetous;</p>
                  <p>One that ruleth well his own houſe, having his children in ſubjection with all gravity.</p>
                  <p>(For if a man know not how to rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take care of the church of God?)</p>
                  <p>Not a novice, leſt being lifted up with pride, he fall into the condemnation of the devil.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, he muſt have a good report of them which are without, leſt he fall into reproach, and the ſnare of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1, 2, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ought thoſe to be qualified that are to be ordained Deacons, for the keeping and diſtributing the common ſtock of the Church?</head>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:169998:81"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Likewiſe muſt the deacons be grave, not double-tongued, not given to much wine, not greedy of filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre,</p>
                  <p>Holding the myſtery of the faith in a pure conſcience.</p>
                  <p>And let theſe alſo firſt be proved, then let them uſe the office of a deacon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found blameleſs.</p>
                  <p>Let the deacons be the husbands of one wife, ruling their children, and their own houſes well. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 8, 9, 10, 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ought their wives to be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Even ſo muſt their wives be grave, not ſlanderers, ſober, faithful in all things. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What direction doth the Apoſtle give touching the caſting of unworthy members out of the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Now we command you, brethren, in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the tradition which ye received of us. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 6.</p>
                  <p>But now have I written unto you,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169998:82"/> not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother, be a fornicator, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner, with ſuch a one no not to eat.</p>
                  <p>For what have I to do to judge them alſo that are without? do not ye judge them that are within?</p>
                  <p>But them that are without, God judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Therefore put away from among your ſelves that wicked perſon. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 11, 12, 13.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Of Baptiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHat is the judgement of John the Baptiſt, of Chriſt Jeſus, and of the Apoſtle Peter touching the doctrine of Baptiſms? How ſpeak they?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I indeed baptize you with water unto repentance: but he that cometh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me is mightier then I, whoſe ſhooes I am not worthy to bear: he ſhall baptize you with the holy Ghoſt, and with fire. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:169998:82"/>
                  <p>Wait for the promiſe of the Father, which ye have heard of me.</p>
                  <p>For John verily baptized with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but ye ſhall be baptized with the holy Ghoſt, not many dayes hence. <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 4, 5.</p>
                  <p>As I began to ſpeak, the holy Ghoſt fell on them, as on us at the beginning.</p>
                  <p>Then remembred I the word of the Lord, how that he ſaid, John indeed baptized with water: but ye ſhall be baptized with the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 15, 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Though the paſſages which you have alledged plainly intimate that the baptiſm of the Spirit was the baptiſm of Chriſt, as that of water was Johns baptiſm, yet did not the Apoſtles of Chriſt baptize with water? what ſaith Paul of this alſo?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I baptized the houſe of Stephanas. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> But divers think the Apoſtles were ſent to baptize as well as to preach. What therefore ſaith the ſame Apoſtle concerning this alſo?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Howbeit when Paul himſelf, and the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169998:83"/> believing Romans were baptized, into what doth he ſay they were baptized, and to what end?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> So many of us as were baptized into Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>were baptized into his death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore we were buried with him by baptiſm into death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed up from the dead by the glory of the Father: <hi>ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſs of life. Rom.</hi> 6. 3, 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Foraſmuch as ſo great ſtreſs is put by ſome upon water-baptiſm, what baptiſm is it, (even in the judgement of the Apoſtle Peter,) whereby we are ſaved; the ſaid baptiſm of water, whereby the filth of the body is waſhed off: or the baptiſm of the heart, whereby it is cleanſed from an evil conſcience?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The like figure whereunto, even baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us; <hi>not the putting away of the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:169998:83"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. <hi>Of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHen was the Lords ſupper inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, and to what end?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Lord Jeſus <hi>the ſame night in which he was betraid,</hi> took bread:</p>
                  <p>And when he had given thanks, he brake it, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my body, which is broken for you: <hi>this do in remembrance of me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After the ſame maner alſo he took the cup, when he had ſupped, ſaying, This cup is the new teſtament in my blood: <hi>this do ye,</hi> as oft as ye drink it, <hi>in remembrance of me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For as oft as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, <hi>ye ſhew forth the Lords death till he come.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23, 24, 25, 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What hurt happeneth to him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth the Lords ſupper unworthily?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Whoſoever ſhall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, ſhall be guilty of the body and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169998:84"/> blood of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>He that eateth and drinketh unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lords body. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 27, 29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall a man behave himſelf, that he may be a worthy communicant at the Lords table?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What examination is it, on which Chriſtians ſhould put themſelves? What ſaith the ſame Apostle concerning this point?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Examine your ſelves, whether you be in the faith: prove your own ſelves. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:169998:84"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>Of the Reſurrection of the dead, and the last Judgement; and what ſhall be the final condition of the righteous and the wicked thereupon.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> WHat do you believe concerning the reſurrection of the dead?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That there ſhall be a reſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt and unjuſt. <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> By whom ſhall the dead be raiſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By Chriſt ſhall all be made alive. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the dead raiſed by Christ, rather then by God himſelf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Since by <hi>man</hi> came death, by man came alſo the reſurrection of the dead. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> How came Christ by this power?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As the Father hath life in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: ſo hath he <hi>given to the Son to have life in himſelf. Joh.</hi> 5. 26.</p>
                  <p>The laſt Adam was <hi>made a quickning</hi>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:169998:85"/> 
                     <hi>ſpirit.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 45.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> By whom ſhall God judge man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 16.</p>
                  <p>He commanded us to preach unto the people, and to teſtifie that it is <hi>he</hi> which was ordained of God to be the judge of quick and dead. <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 42.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What aſſurance hath God given that he will judge the world by this man?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In that he hath raiſed him from the dead. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 31.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What ſhall be the different iſſue of the good from that of the bad at the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All that are in the graves ſhall come forth; they that have done good, to the reſurrection of life; and they that have done evil, unto the reſurrection of damnation. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 28, 29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Shall not the wicked and unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing live for ever, (though in torments,) as well as the godly and the faithful? or is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life peculiar to the faithful?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He that believeth on the Son, hath everlaſting life: and he that believeth
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169998:85"/> not the Son, <hi>ſhall not ſee life:</hi> but the warth of God abideth on him. <hi>John</hi> 3. 36.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Though this paſſage which you have cited ſeem clearly to prove that eternal life agreeth unto no other men, but the faithful: yet ſince the contrary opinion is generally held amongſt Chriſtians, I would fain know farther of you, whether you have any other places that directly affirm that the wicked <hi>dye,</hi> and that <hi>a ſecond death; are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction; are corrupted, burnt-up, devoured, ſlain, paſs away, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The wages of ſin <hi>is death:</hi> but the gift of God <hi>is eternal life, Rom.</hi> 6. 23.</p>
                  <p>If ye live after the fleſh, <hi>ye ſhall dye:</hi> but if ye through the Spirit mortifie the deeds of the body, <hi>ye ſhall live. Rom.</hi> 8. 13.</p>
                  <p>I will give unto him that is athriſt, of the fountain <hi>of the water of life</hi> freely.</p>
                  <p>But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murtherers, and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and all lyars, ſhall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169998:86"/> and brimſtone: <hi>which is the ſecond death. Rev.</hi> 21. 6, 8.</p>
                  <p>Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee <hi>the crown of life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that overcometh ſhall not be hurt <hi>of the ſecond death. Rev.</hi> 2. 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>When they ſhall ſay, Peace and ſafety: then <hi>ſudden deſtruction</hi> cometh upon them, as travel upon a woman with child; and they ſhall not eſcape. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
                  <p>The day of judgement, and <hi>perdition of ungodly men.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 7.</p>
                  <p>The Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from heaven with his mighty angels,</p>
                  <p>In flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 7, 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>He that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap <hi>corruption:</hi> but he that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reap <hi>life everlaſting. Gal.</hi> 6. 8.</p>
                  <p>Theſe as natural bruit beaſts made to be taken and deſtroyed, ſpeak evil of the things that they underſtand not, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169998:86"/> ſhall <hi>utterly periſh</hi> in their corruption. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
                  <p>If any man defile the temple of God, him ſhall God <hi>deſtroy.</hi> Gr. <hi>corrupt.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 17.</p>
                  <p>We are not of them that draw back <hi>to perdition:</hi> but of them that believe <hi>to the ſaving of the ſoul. Heb.</hi> 10. 39.</p>
                  <p>Which the unlearned and unſtable wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>unto their own deſtruction.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
                  <p>Whoſe fan is in his hand, and he will throughly purge his floor, and gather his wheat into the garner: but he <hi>will burn up the chaff</hi> with unquenchable fire. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 12.</p>
                  <p>If we ſin wilfully after that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſins,</p>
                  <p>But a certain fearful looking for of judgement, and fiery indignation (Gr. fervor of fire) <hi>which ſhall devour the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. Heb.</hi> 10. 26, 27.</p>
                  <p>But thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould raign over them, bring hither, and <hi>ſlay them before me. Luke</hi> 19. 27.</p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:169998:87"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The world paſſeth away,</hi> and the luſts thereof: but he that doth the will of God, <hi>abideth for ever.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 17.</p>
                  <p>We are unto God a ſweet ſavor of Chriſt, in them that are ſaved, and <hi>in them that periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the one we are the ſavor of death unto death; and to the other the ſavor of life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 15, 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the uſe that our Saviour himſelf would have us make of this doctrine touching the deſtruction of men in hell-fire?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Fear him which is able to deſtroy both ſoul and body in hell. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> In what maner ſhall Chriſt come and adminiſter judgement at the laſt day?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the Son of man ſhall come in his glory, and all the holy angels with him, then ſhall he ſit upon the throne of his glory.</p>
                  <p>And before him ſhall be gathered all Nations, and he ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as a ſhepherd divideth his ſheep from the goats.</p>
                  <p>And he ſhall ſet the ſheep on his right hand, but the goats on the left.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169998:87"/> Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</p>
                  <p>For I was an hungred, and ye gave me meat: I was thirſty, and ye gave me drink: I was a ſtranger, and ye took me in:</p>
                  <p>Naked, and ye clothed me: I was ſick, and ye viſited me: I was in priſon, and ye came unto me.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall the righteous anſwer him, ſaying, Lord, when ſaw we thee an hungred, and fed thee? thriſty, and gave thee drink?</p>
                  <p>When ſaw we thee a ſtranger, and took thee in? or naked, and clothed thee?</p>
                  <p>Or when ſaw we thee ſick, or in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and came unto thee?</p>
                  <p>And the King ſhall anſwer, and ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, Verily I ſay unto you, Inaſmuch as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren, ye have done it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall he ſay alſo unto them on the left hand, Depart from me, ye curſed, into everlaſting fire, prepared for the divel and his angels.</p>
                  <p>For I was an hungred, and ye gave me
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:169998:88"/> no meat: I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink:</p>
                  <p>I was a ſtranger, and ye took me not in: naked, and ye clothed me not: ſick, and in priſon, and ye viſited me not.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall they alſo anſwer him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Lord, when ſaw we thee an hungred, or athirſt, or a ſtranger, or naked, or ſick, or in priſon, and did not miniſter unto thee?</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall he anſwer them, ſaying, Verily I ſay unto you, Inaſmuch as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me.</p>
                  <p>And theſe ſhall go away into everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting puniſhment: but the righteous into life eternal. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 31, 32, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Is there not another reſurrection and judgement that ſhall precede this laſt and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral one, and peculiarly belongeth unto the ſaints that have been ſlain for the teſtimony of Jeſus, and for the word of God? what ſaith John the Divine concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I ſaw thrones, and they ſate upon them, and judgement was given to them: and I ſaw the ſouls of them that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed for the witneſs of Jeſus, and for
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:169998:88"/> the word of God, and which had not worſhipped the Beaſt, neither his image, neither had received his mark upon their foreheads, or in their hands; and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</p>
                  <p>But the reſt of the dead lived not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain until the thouſand years were finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This is the firſt reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed and holy is he that hath part in the firſt reſurrection: on ſuch the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death hath no power, but they ſhall be prieſts of God and of Chriſt, and ſhall reign with him a thouſand years. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 4, 5, 6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
